<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons one against adultery, the other of the nature, art, and issue of the Christian warfare : with a discourse shewing the consistency of God's infinite goodness with His foreknowledge of the fall of man / by Nathanael Whaley ...</title>
            <author>Whaley, Nathanael, 1637?-1709.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 71 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96272</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1533A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09431672</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09431672</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151439</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96272)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151439)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1319:26 or 2259:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons one against adultery, the other of the nature, art, and issue of the Christian warfare : with a discourse shewing the consistency of God's infinite goodness with His foreknowledge of the fall of man / by Nathanael Whaley ...</title>
                  <author>Whaley, Nathanael, 1637?-1709.</author>
                  <author>Whaley, Nathanael, 1637?-1709. A discourse shewing the consistency of God's infinite goodness with His foreknowledge of the fall of man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>144 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Brab. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This item appears at reel 1319:26 incorrectly identified as Wing W1533, and at reel 2259:7 as Wing (2nd ed.) W1533A.</note>
                  <note>"A discourse shewing the consistency of God's infinite goodness with His foreknowledge of the fall of man" (p. 109-144) has special t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: copy at reel 2259:7 lacks p. 97-106.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Harvard University Library and British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Temptation --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>TWO SERMONS: One againſt ADULTERY; The Other, of the NATURE, ART, and ISSUE Of the <hi>Chriſtian Warfare.</hi> WITH A DISCOURSE, Shewing the CONSISTENCY of God's Infinite Goodneſs With his <hi>Foreknowledge</hi> of the <hi>FALL</hi> of <hi>MAN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL WHALEY,</hi> A. M. Rector of <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.H.</hi> for <hi>Brab. Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1698.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151439:2"/>
                  <head>A SERMON AGAINST <hi>ADULTERY.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Gen. XXXIX. 9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>— How then can I do this great Wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God?</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>IN the ſeven and thirtieth Chapter of this moſt <hi>Ancient</hi> and <hi>Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Hiſtory, <hi>Moſes,</hi> the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Author of it, is very exact in relating the various and wonderfull <hi>turns</hi> of Providence, which brought <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>Potiphar</hi>'s Houſe; and here he leaves him, till he has given an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome Miſcarriages in the life of <hi>Judah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ch. <hi>38.</hi>
                     </note> which he draws with its <hi>Shades</hi> and <hi>Blemiſhes</hi> amongſt the <hi>brighter</hi> and <hi>fairer</hi> Paſſages of it. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this,<note place="margin">Ch. <hi>39.</hi>
                     </note> he reſumes the Story of <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151439:3"/>and acquaints us with his cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Entertainment in <hi>Potiphar's</hi> houſe, with the great <hi>Truſt</hi> his Maſter repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in him, the mighty <hi>Reputation</hi> he gain'd by his prudent and faithfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, the <hi>ſtrange</hi> Succeſs which attended all his Undertakings, his <hi>grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> Remembrance of the <hi>ſignal</hi> Honours and Favours his <hi>munificent</hi> Patron had conferr'd upon him: And to compleat his <hi>Character,</hi> the Divine Hiſtorian tells you of his eminent virtue in defeating the <hi>perfidious</hi> and <hi>lewd</hi> Deſires of his <hi>amorous</hi> and <hi>importunate</hi> Miſtreſs, whoſe wicked and ſhameleſs <hi>Courtſhips</hi> he daſht with this <hi>ſhort</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> Anſwer, <hi>How then can I do this great Wickedneſs, and ſin againſt God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the words the moſt obvious and material things are theſe two:</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Sentiment of Adultery, or the Violation of the Conjugal Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>viz.</hi> that it is a great Wickedneſs and Offence againſt God.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The excellent uſe he made of it, which was to repel the rude <hi>Inſults</hi> of his <hi>ſalacious</hi> Miſtreſs, and free himſelf from the danger of ſinning with her.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151439:3"/>
                     <hi>How then can I do this great Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> &amp;c. As if he had ſaid, I can never conſent to ſo <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>vile</hi> an action as you tempt me to; a thing never to be anſwered to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man:</hi> the <hi>God,</hi> whom from my Infancy I was taught to <hi>fear,</hi> by whoſe Providence I was conducted under your <hi>hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Roof: Or the <hi>good Man</hi> that has <hi>nobly</hi> cheriſht my Ambition, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded my poor endeavours to ſerve him. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> you ſee, had a <hi>preſent</hi> and lively ſenſe of the <hi>Horrour</hi> of the Crime he was tempted to: and this was apparently owing to his <hi>religious</hi> Education, by which his mind was ſtrongly <hi>impregnated</hi> with the <hi>Fear of God:</hi> and having theſe advantages, he eaſily overcame the <hi>ſurprizing Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and ſo doing, has happily left us theſe three Inſtructions.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. That the ſtrongeſt Temptations to the moſt flattering and deceitfull Vices are not <hi>invincible.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. That a <hi>good Education</hi> is a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty advantage towards the leading a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and unſpotted Life, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming the greateſt Temptations to Vice and Wickedneſs.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151439:4"/>
                  <p n="3">III. That <hi>the Fear of God</hi> quickned with a <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>lively</hi> Apprehenſion of the great evil of Sin, is a ſovereign and effectual <hi>Preſervative</hi> againſt the moſt charming and powerfull Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to it.</p>
                  <p>To each of theſe Particulars I ſhall ſpeak in their order: and firſt of</p>
                  <p n="1">I. <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Sentiment of <hi>Adultery,</hi> or the Violation of the Conjugal Union, which he deſervedly calls a <hi>great Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs and Offence againſt God.</hi> And this, I doubt not, will appear from <hi>Principles</hi> generally allowed for the moſt exact and authentick <hi>Meaſures</hi> of <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil:</hi> ſuch as <hi>the Light of Nature,</hi> the declared <hi>ſenſe of Mankind</hi> concerning the intrinſick <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>Turpitude</hi> of Actions, the Authority of <hi>Divine Revelation,</hi> and the <hi>natural Tendency</hi> of things (verified by <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Experience</hi>) to produce good or bad effects in the World. If men will diſpute ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> as theſe, I have nothing at preſent to ſay to them, but that they may do well no longer to diſſemble their <hi>Sentiments,</hi> but play upon the <hi>Square,</hi> and fairly tell the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151439:4"/>World, they know no difference in the <hi>Nature</hi> of Actions, but what is <hi>made</hi> by the preſent Senſe or Remembrance of <hi>Pain</hi> or <hi>Pleaſure:</hi> That Mankind is <hi>degenerated</hi> by aſpiring to <hi>better Manners</hi> than the Brutes: and that they are not at all <hi>ambitious</hi> to retain to that <hi>order</hi> of Beings, that muſt needs <hi>diſtinguiſh</hi> themſelves from their <hi>Fellow-Creatures</hi> by a <hi>lofty</hi> Pretence to <hi>Reaſon and Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My Buſineſs, at preſent, is with men of a <hi>better rank,</hi> I mean ſuch as are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the <hi>true Worth</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of humane Nature, and that the <hi>worſt</hi> part of it (the Body) is much too <hi>good</hi> to be inſlaved to <hi>obſcene</hi> and <hi>unworthy</hi> Luſts, and dragg'd through all the <hi>Filth</hi> and <hi>Diſhonour</hi> of a madly voluptuous Life; who when they are tempted to a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch,</hi> or overſet by a <hi>violent</hi> Appetite to unlawfull Pleaſures, do ſmartly feel a <hi>controuling Principle</hi> within them; or if they have been <hi>overtaken in a Fault,</hi> do yet retain a <hi>bluſhing Senſe</hi> of Virtue and Religion, are willing to underſtand <hi>their Errors,</hi> to be remind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the <hi>danger</hi> of them, and to be armed againſt the worſt that may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall them for the future. And ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151439:5"/>Perſons will, I hope, in kindneſs to <hi>themſelves,</hi> have the Patience and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity to conſider,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Character in the Text is agreeable to the <hi>general Senſe</hi> of Mankind, eſpecially of the moſt <hi>refined</hi> and <hi>civilized</hi> Nations. For that this was no <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> Notion of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily or Religion of <hi>Abraham,</hi> is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s Diſcourſe with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 12.18, 19. Gen. 20.9, 10. Gen. 39.20.</note> and <hi>Abimelech</hi>'s on the like occaſion; and by <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s <hi>Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to hide the Naughtineſs of his Miſtreſs, who with an Impudence <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar</hi> to her character, vehemently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed him of attempting her Chaſtity. By theſe Teſtimonies, it is plain that <hi>Adultery</hi> was eſteem'd <hi>a great Sin</hi> in the Courts of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and theſe are ſome of the moſt <hi>ancient Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> we read of in <hi>authentick</hi> Hiſtories. And indeed in all Countries, from the firſt <hi>Dawn</hi> of Learning and Civility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them (not excepting thoſe that pretend to greater Antiquity) it has ever had an <hi>ill Name,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">China, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, Peru.</note> and is generally lookt upon as one of the <hi>rankeſt</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries and Corruptions of humane Nature. As ſuch, it was condemned long before <hi>the Diſtinction</hi> of Heathens,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151439:5"/>Jews, and Chriſtians: and ever ſince by the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> Nations, that had nothing but the <hi>weak Taper</hi> of Nature to <hi>guide</hi> them. And therefore it muſt be <hi>evil in it ſelf;</hi> for the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers nothing to be <hi>evil,</hi> but what is <hi>evil</hi> in its <hi>own Nature:</hi> and what is ſo muſt be <hi>evil</hi> in all Ages, Perſons, and Circumſtances. Nor does the practice of this Vice, <hi>without controul,</hi> in ſome <hi>wild</hi> and <hi>barbarous</hi> Nations, overthrow the force of this Argument, any more than the <hi>Toleration</hi> of other Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in ſome <hi>dark</hi> Ages and Countries, or the open <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of groſs and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable <hi>Errors,</hi> proves the <hi>Rectitude</hi> of ſuch Actions and Errors, or will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their Contrariety to right <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> 'Tis enough to juſtifie the Cenſure in the Text, that it agrees with the <hi>beſt</hi> and <hi>general</hi> Reaſon of Mankind.</p>
                  <p>And this, methinks, ſhould ſatisfie thoſe Men, who laying aſide all <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> depend upon <hi>natural Reaſon</hi> as the <hi>onely Guide</hi> and Director of their Thoughts and Actions; there being nothing <hi>plainer</hi> in the Eye of <hi>natural Reaſon,</hi> than that the actions which are <hi>contrary</hi> to it are <hi>evil,</hi> and will be ſo,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151439:6"/>as long as there is a <hi>rational Nature.</hi> That is, God has framed the Nature of <hi>Man</hi> ſo agreeably to his <hi>own Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> as to ſhew him what is <hi>eſſentially good and evil</hi> by the <hi>Light</hi> of his <hi>own Reaſon,</hi> and to ſtamp the Dictates of it as <hi>a Law</hi> upon his Mind; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sins comitted againſt <hi>this Law</hi> muſt be great Offences <hi>againſt God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is both the <hi>Maker</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and of the <hi>Nature</hi> he deſigned to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern by it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Adultery violates the <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> of Marriage, which laid the <hi>Foundation</hi> of all humane Society, was deſigned to perpetuate the <hi>Race</hi> of Mankind, and unite Men by the moſt <hi>natural Tyes</hi> and <hi>Endearments</hi> in all <hi>friendly</hi> Offices, and in the ſolemn <hi>Worſhip</hi> and Adorations of God. The Union of <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Woman</hi> in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal State was ordained for theſe <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</hi> ends; which, conſidering the <hi>preſent Conſtitution</hi> of humane Nature, are no leſs neceſſary to our <hi>Happineſs</hi> in <hi>this</hi> World, than the Bleſſed <hi>Society</hi> of glorious <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels</hi> is to the Happineſs of the <hi>next.</hi> And accordingly this was one of the tranſcendent Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of <hi>Paradice,</hi> without which the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151439:6"/>
                     <hi>Garden of Eden,</hi> with its <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> Variety of all other <hi>Comforts</hi> and <hi>Conveniencies</hi> of Life, had been more like a <hi>Deſert,</hi> than <hi>a Paradice,</hi> to any <hi>ſingle</hi> Poſſeſſor of it. For if we look into the <hi>Frame</hi> of our Nature, and conſider how eſſential <hi>Amity</hi> and <hi>Friendſhip</hi> are to the <hi>Felicity</hi> of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creature, or that <hi>Greatneſs of Soul</hi> Man (the deſigned <hi>Emperour</hi> of this lower World) was liberally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed withal, when firſt he came out of his <hi>Maker</hi>'s hand, it was plainly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for <hi>Man to be alone</hi> and be <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py.</hi> For to be <hi>happy</hi> is not to have more <hi>good</hi> in view than we can graſp or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; This may make us <hi>miſerable,</hi> but can never make us <hi>happy.</hi> To be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, is to have all things <hi>ſuitable</hi> to our <hi>juſt</hi> Deſires: and what can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine more <hi>deſirable</hi> to Man in his <hi>ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> ſtate of Innocence, than to have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his own <hi>Shape</hi> and <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> capable of converſing with him, and, by <hi>dividing,</hi> of <hi>encreaſing</hi> his Joys? and then if God had denied him this <hi>conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient help,</hi> after he had made him <hi>meet</hi> for Society, and exchanges of Love and Kindneſs, he would certainly have been apt to <hi>languiſh,</hi> and (like a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151439:7"/>Lover in the <hi>Abſence</hi> of his peculiar Delight) to complain to the Winds and Fountains, or the mated Birds and Beaſts, of his <hi>unket</hi> and <hi>loneſome</hi> State, and to grow <hi>melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> upon the Walks of <hi>Paradice,</hi> while he had all the <hi>Treaſures,</hi> and all the <hi>ſilent Beauties</hi> of Nature about him, and wanted nothing but <hi>another ſelf</hi> to reliſh and complete his Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>And this ſhews the ſtate of <hi>Marriage</hi> to be <hi>Honourable,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note> and conſiſtent with the higheſt degrees of <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> in our preſent Circumſtances: And that it was appointed for <hi>a general good,</hi> and for one of the choiceſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and Entertainments of Life. The <hi>Time, Place,</hi> and <hi>Author</hi> of this Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution are undeniable Arguments of its <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and the Reaſon it was founded upon, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe <hi>it was not good for man to be alone,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commends the <hi>Conjugal State</hi> as good and convenient in all Ages,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.18.</note> and to Perſons of all Ranks and Qualities that are ſenſible of the want of this <hi>Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Society.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151439:7"/>
                  <p>'Tis farther obſervable, as an <hi>inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible</hi> mark of the <hi>Sanctity</hi> of this Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, that it was immediately decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by God himſelf;<note place="margin">Gen. 2.24.</note> and at the ſame time was ſignally <hi>honoured</hi> (as is thought by very learned Interpreters) with the glorious Appearance of the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> attended with the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Hoſt,</hi> at the happy <hi>Eſpouſals</hi> of our Firſt Parents. And, we know, when any occaſion was offered to <hi>our Saviour</hi> of ſpeaking to this Argument,<note place="margin">Matth. 19.3, 4, 5.</note> that he conſtantly affirm'd the <hi>Sacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the Marriage-Union, as ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the <hi>original</hi> Inſtitution; and that he choſe to grace the Wedding in <hi>Cana of Galilee</hi> with his <hi>firſt Miracle.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 2.1. &amp;c.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now to <hi>violate</hi> this dear and ſacred Union by <hi>Adulterous</hi> Mixtures, is a perfect Contradiction to the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of God, and the <hi>kind</hi> Proviſion he has made for the <hi>Harmony</hi> of the World; it is an <hi>inſolent</hi> Contempt of his <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty</hi> over his Creatures, of his <hi>right</hi> to fix them in their ſeveral <hi>Stations,</hi> and appoint them <hi>their bounds which they ſhall not paſs,</hi> to limit their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to their <hi>proper</hi> Objects, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them from invading the <hi>Rights,</hi> and raviſhing the <hi>reſerv'd</hi> and <hi>incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151439:8"/>Treaſures of each other. For what greater inſolence can there be, than to diſpute the <hi>Government</hi> of the World with the <hi>Maker</hi> of it? To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the <hi>Bounds</hi> of Entercourſe and Society, which the Wiſdom of God hath eſtabliſht <hi>from the Beginning,</hi> and <hi>proſtitute</hi> his Holy Inſtitutions to the Gratification of a <hi>lawleſs</hi> and <hi>brutiſh</hi> Appetite? Was ever any Law given to Men more <hi>plainly</hi> worded, more <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly</hi> publiſht, <hi>edg'd</hi> and inforc'd with <hi>ſharper</hi> Threatnings, or more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inculcated by the Prophets and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of God, than this, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit Adultery?</hi> The Violation therefore of <hi>this Law</hi> muſt be highly diſhonourable and offenſive to him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is an act of ſhamefull Turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Impurity <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> It ſtains the Image of God upon the <hi>Soul,</hi> and defiles the <hi>Body;</hi> both which being <hi>conſecrated</hi> to God's peculiar Service in our <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> are properly ſtyled his <hi>Temple</hi> in Scripture;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Know ye not</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that your Body is the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, which is in you?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.17.</note> And <hi>if any man defile the Temple of God, him will God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: for the Temple of God is holy,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151439:8"/>which Temple ye are.</hi> And then Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Adultery are no <hi>common Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions</hi> in a Chriſtian, but high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of <hi>Prophanation</hi> and <hi>Impiety:</hi> Tell it not to the Heathen World; they are certainly, next to Idolatry, the moſt <hi>ſacrilegious Abuſes</hi> of the beſt things <hi>devoted</hi> to God's peculiar Service and Honour. For Chriſtians are not only <hi>the Temple of the living God</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them) but they are his <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> and <hi>moſt holy Temple;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.16.</note> His <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Houſe,</hi> in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Phraſe,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5, 9.</note> nay his <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Royal Prieſthood,</hi> ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>to offer up Spiritual Sacrifices, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So that for a Chriſtian to defile himſelf with <hi>fleſhly Luſts,</hi> is to add <hi>Prophaneſs to Impurity.</hi> It is to defile at once God's <hi>Temple, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Altar,</hi> and to make his beſt <hi>Sacrifices</hi> loathſome and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable to him; to obſtruct all <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>amicable</hi> Entercourſe between God and him, and to <hi>grieve</hi> and diſcharge his holy and ever Bleſſed Spirit, that <hi>Divine Gueſt</hi> whom he hath ſent to <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with us for ever,</hi> and to <hi>ſanctifie,</hi> and <hi>ſeal us to the Day of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151439:9"/>
                  <p n="4">4. Adultery is a Crime of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Baſeneſs</hi> and <hi>Treachery</hi> towards our <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> Neighbour. There is ſuch a Complication of Evils, ſo much palpable <hi>Injuſtice, Infamy</hi> and <hi>Falſhood</hi> in every act of this Sin, that it is commonly reckoned by the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Relations of the <hi>offending</hi> Parties, that have any <hi>Sparks</hi> of Honour or Virtue in them, one of the ſharpeſt Tryals of <hi>Patience,</hi> one of the <hi>heavieſt Croſſes</hi> and Afflictions that are incident to them in this World. By this means the <hi>good Man</hi> is not only deprived (contrary to all Law and Equity) of his certain and apparent Rights; but he is ſhamefully <hi>betrayed</hi> and <hi>ſupplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in his <hi>choiceſt</hi> and moſt valuable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts; things of that extremely <hi>nice, tender,</hi> and <hi>peculiar</hi> Nature, that it is hardly poſſible to compute the vaſt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries</hi> he ſuffers by the Invader of them; ſuch are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Virtue and Fidelity of his Wife; to be wrong'd in whom, and bereaved of that ſingular <hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Complacency</hi> which flows from the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of a <hi>chaſt</hi> and <hi>faithfull</hi> Conſort, is to loſe the <hi>Flower</hi> of his Happineſs in this World. And be ſure the more kind
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151439:9"/>and virtuous the <hi>good Man</hi> is, the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is his Pain and Anguiſh to behold <hi>the delight of his Eyes</hi> raviſht from his own into the <hi>circle</hi> of a Strangers arms, there by wicked <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> beguiled of her <hi>Innocence,</hi> and transform'd into a <hi>loathſome</hi> and <hi>perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious</hi> Creature. For what perſon can be more <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>nauſeous</hi> (how fair ſoever in her Looks and Pretences) or more wretchedly <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>treacherous</hi> than ſhe, that in Contempt of her <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar-Vows,</hi> her moſt <hi>ſolemn</hi> and <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Promiſes, before God and the World, of <hi>untainted</hi> Loyalty and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to her Husband, conſents to the <hi>lewdeſt</hi> Practices, and commits the <hi>fouleſt</hi> Treaſons aganſt him! That with her <hi>veil</hi> of Modeſty <hi>caſts off</hi> all regard to the <hi>Honour</hi> of her Religion, her Birth, and Family, <hi>proſtitutes</hi> her ſelf to a mean and ignoble Paſſion, and forſakes the <hi>Cryſtal Stream</hi> of Conjugal and Chaſt Enjoyments, to wallow in the <hi>Mire</hi> and <hi>Puddle</hi> of diſhoneſt and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Pleaſure!<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.6.</note> 
                     <hi>She that lives in Pleaſure</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>is dead while ſhe lives.</hi> And certainly 'tis the worſt kind of Death <hi>ante mortem perire</hi> (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>to periſh alive,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ep. 93.</note> 
                     <hi>and meet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151439:10"/>Corruption</hi> on this ſide the Grave, as many of the <hi>wild Lovers of Pleaſure</hi> chuſe to do, rather than lead (as they eſteem it) a <hi>dull, virtuous</hi> life; the mean while they are <hi>dead</hi> to all the <hi>good purpoſes</hi> of <hi>living,</hi> and not only ſo, but <hi>live</hi> in a ſtate of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Putrefaction;</hi> they feel themſelves <hi>rotting</hi> and <hi>periſhing</hi> before their time, till their Life grows a <hi>Burden</hi> to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and a <hi>Nuſance</hi> to all that are about them; As if they only came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to <hi>annoy</hi> it, and had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived to do the <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Buſineſs</hi> of the Grave, before they deſcend into it.</p>
                  <p>Such is the Tendency of this <hi>perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> Courſe, the very entrance into which, as it often proves, is more than <hi>half</hi> the way to the <hi>Depths of Hell:</hi> and then it muſt needs grieve the heart of any <hi>Generous</hi> and good-natured Man, to ſee <hi>the Wife of his Boſom,</hi> whom he <hi>loved as his own Soul,</hi> and cheriſht as his <hi>own Fleſh,</hi> ſo far <hi>engaged</hi> and ſo miſerably <hi>loſt</hi> in the <hi>Paths</hi> of Vice and Ruin, and to loſe <hi>one half</hi> of his Life and Happineſs by her vile <hi>Apoſtaſie.</hi> To give the true <hi>Accent</hi> to ſuch a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as this, when it firſt <hi>throbs</hi> and <hi>beats</hi> againſt the Breaſt that is <hi>delug'd</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151439:10"/>with it, is not in the power of <hi>Eloquence:</hi> Nature only can do it by <hi>inimitable</hi> Sighs and Pangs, whilſt the greateſt degrees of <hi>Grace</hi> are little enough to bear up <hi>the Spirit</hi> of Man, under ſo <hi>preſſing</hi> and <hi>unwieldy</hi> a Calamity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His own Reputation and Honour ſuffer greatly by this foul and treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Act. For tho' the <hi>good Man</hi> never expos'd himſelf to the <hi>Cenſure</hi> of the world; tho' it may be he has all the <hi>true Principles</hi> of Honour, Prudence, and Integrity in him, and the worſt that can be ſaid of him is; <hi>the poor Man was unhappy in his Choice:</hi> yet ſuch is the <hi>ill-Nature</hi> of the World, and <hi>the Levity</hi> of vain people (who muſt be ever talking of the Crimes, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining themſelves with the Misfortunes of their Neighbours) that he is ſure to be <hi>upbraided</hi> with his Calamity, and to have his <hi>good Name</hi> bandied in Sport and Scurrility: and perhaps a great deal more than if he had <hi>blacken'd</hi> it himſelf with <hi>Vice,</hi> or had not provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a perverſe and <hi>adulterous Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> by <hi>daring</hi> to be chaſt and virtuous in it. 'Tis very unnatural, I am ſure, to jeer and raily upon mens <hi>Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,</hi> i.e. to abuſe my Neighbour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151439:11"/>merely for being <hi>unhappy,</hi> and leave him nothing but his <hi>Innocence</hi> to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and comfort him: to <hi>revive</hi> his ſorrows, and keep his mind upon the <hi>rack,</hi> when he needs the very <hi>kindeſt</hi> and <hi>tendereſt</hi> Uſage I can poſſibly give him. And this, as <hi>light</hi> a matter as it ſeems, we cannot but obſerve, is very <hi>hard</hi> upon the <hi>ſufferer</hi> in the preſent Caſe; nay, is often reputed one of the moſt <hi>grievous</hi> Circumſtances in his ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull and uneaſie Condition.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He is continually liable to be teaz'd and tortur'd with <hi>the Spirit of Jealouſie.</hi> And ſurely there is not a greater <hi>Torment</hi> to any <hi>Candid</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Perſon: But when it ſeizes a Man of <hi>high</hi> and <hi>violent</hi> Paſſions, what ſtrange <hi>Combuſtion</hi> does it make in his <hi>Spirit!</hi> He is inſtantly <hi>all in a Flame,</hi> his Breaſt <hi>glows,</hi> his Heart <hi>burns</hi> with Revenge, his Eyes <hi>flaſh</hi> with Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not to be <hi>quench'd</hi> with his <hi>own</hi> or the <hi>Tears</hi> of his <hi>compaſſionate Friends;</hi> now he appears like a perfect <hi>Fury,</hi> fierce and inexorable; Curſes his <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal Day,</hi> nay the <hi>Day</hi> in which he was <hi>born;</hi> Then thinks of a thouſand <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges,</hi> but knows not <hi>which</hi> to purſue, till ſome <hi>unlucky Accident</hi> determines
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151439:11"/>his choice; and then, if he either <hi>falls ſhort</hi> of his Deſign, or <hi>over-acts</hi> it with Rage and Cruelty, he preſently turns <hi>pale</hi> like a <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> ſlarts and trembles at every <hi>ſhadow,</hi> as if every thing that approacht him <hi>now,</hi> came to upbraid him with his Folly or Miſery.</p>
                  <p>I don't ſay this is the <hi>conſtant</hi> or the <hi>onely</hi> effect of <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> it being true of this as of all other <hi>Diſtempers</hi> of the Mind, that it varies according to the <hi>different Complexion</hi> of the Patient, and the good or bad Habits his Mind is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht or infeſted with. And hence <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie</hi> (as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> obſerves) has two very <hi>contrary</hi> effects, which he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>;<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, Cap. <hi>52.</hi>
                     </note> the <hi>firſt</hi> is ſuch a <hi>Dulneſs</hi> and <hi>Heavineſs of Mind,</hi> as makes a man perfectly <hi>ſtupid</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible</hi> of all things but his <hi>proper grief:</hi> The <hi>other</hi> is inſatiate <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Fury,</hi> always prompting and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him to <hi>haſten</hi> and <hi>ſignalize</hi> his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; not to be <hi>diſcouraged</hi> with dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, nor <hi>ſoften'd</hi> with Intreaties; not to be <hi>pacified</hi> with the <hi>deepeſt</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions; not to be ſatisfied with the <hi>largeſt</hi> Overtures; not ſo much as to wait the Leaſure of <hi>publick Juſtice,</hi> but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his <hi>own Methods,</hi> purſue his <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151439:12"/>with the <hi>utmoſt</hi> Severity, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the ſpeedieſt and ſharpeſt <hi>Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> upon him. And this <hi>Solomon</hi> long ſince obſerved, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.34, 35. <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie is the rage of a Man: therefore he will not ſpare in the day of Vengeance. He will not regard any Ranſom, neither will he reſt content, tho' thou giveſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny gifts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The good man is greatly wrong'd in the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Intereſts</hi> of his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,</hi> his innocent Children ſuffering with their abuſed Father, and <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the vaſt Infelicities, their <hi>lewd</hi> Mother hath liberally <hi>entail'd</hi> upon them. 'Tis their unhappineſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend from a <hi>naughty</hi> and <hi>perfidious</hi> Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, to want the Influence of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> in their tender Years, and it may be to derive a <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>ill-addicted</hi> Nature from her, a <hi>tainted Conſtitution</hi> of Mind and Body, inſtead of the <hi>true Principles</hi> of a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and happy Life. 'Tis their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Grief to obſerve the <hi>Jarrs</hi> and <hi>Diſſentions</hi> of their divided Parents, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when they come to learn the <hi>diſmal</hi> occaſion of them, and behold their Eſtate and Patrimony <hi>melting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> between the unnatural <hi>Heats</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151439:12"/>Contention, and the prodigal <hi>Flames</hi> of Luſt. 'Tis their wrong to have the <hi>Brood</hi> of the Adulterer cheriſht and brought up with them, who through the <hi>Subtilty</hi> of her that bare him is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten made <hi>the Darling</hi> of the Family, and too often goes away with <hi>a fairer Portion</hi> than any of the <hi>Legitimate</hi> Children of it.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the <hi>genuine</hi> and moſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Effects of this <hi>rampant</hi> and <hi>furious</hi> Luſt. Theſe are the <hi>kindneſſes</hi> of the falſe Adulterer to his <hi>harmleſs unthink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Neighbour, while he carries on his <hi>amorous Plots</hi> againſt him with the <hi>faireſt</hi> Pretences, and the <hi>higheſt</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of Love and Friendſhip to him and his Family; a <hi>Love</hi> more <hi>fatal</hi> than <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> than the <hi>Grave;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to its <hi>deareſt</hi> Object, againſt which it levels its <hi>fieryeſt Darts,</hi> and for which it reſerves the deepeſt and ſoreſt Ruine. Its very <hi>firſt</hi> Wound is <hi>deadly</hi> and deſperately <hi>cruel;</hi> the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity</hi> of a Wife being <hi>deſervedly</hi> eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at a much higher Value than the brighteſt and moſt charming <hi>Beauty,</hi> the fineſt and pleaſanteſt <hi>Wit,</hi> the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Dowry,</hi> or even the ſweeteſt and moſt agreeable <hi>Mien</hi> and <hi>Temper.</hi> And
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151439:13"/>the Reaſon why men generally ſet <hi>a greater price</hi> upon this than other <hi>good Properties</hi> is, becauſe of all others it is moſt <hi>eſſential</hi> to Conjugal <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion;</hi> inſomuch that the Violation of this <hi>one,</hi> breaks the whole <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>amicable</hi> and <hi>ſocial</hi> Virtues, without which no Society, tho founded upon <hi>Divine</hi> Inſtitution, can poſſibly hold and be <hi>happy.</hi> And this doubtleſs was the reaſon why <hi>our Saviour,</hi> who was <hi>infinitely</hi> tender of the Rights of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,<note place="margin">Matth, 19.9.</note> gave the Jews a liberty of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorce</hi> in the <hi>deſperate</hi> Caſe of Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. The <hi>want</hi> of ſome Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in a <hi>Loyal Conſort</hi> may be made up by a <hi>Plenitude</hi> of other <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Advantages:</hi> but the <hi>Loſs</hi> of Chaſtity can never be repaired in kind or value; No <hi>equivalent</hi> can be given for it, the <hi>ſtolen</hi> Treaſure can never be reſtored; the Flower that is <hi>blaſted,</hi> can never recover its verdant Beauty.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. I might add to this heavy Charge, that Adultery is highly injurious to the <hi>common good</hi> and welfare of Men. The Contention it <hi>kindles</hi> in a private Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily is ſeldom <hi>extinguiſht</hi> there, but frequently breaks out, <hi>alarms</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames</hi> the Neighbourhood into Riots
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151439:13"/>and Factions, to the Diſturbance of the <hi>publick</hi> Peace, the levying of <hi>war,</hi> and the Subverſion (ſometimes) of <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> and <hi>Governments;</hi> to the <hi>grief</hi> of all good men, and the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>boldeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>impudent</hi> Vices. It were endleſs to reckon up the <hi>Judgments</hi> and <hi>Calamities</hi> which this Sin alone has brought upon the World. Who can count the <hi>Treaſure</hi> it has waſted, or tell how much <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> it has betrayed, how many <hi>Duels</hi> it has fought, how many <hi>Lives</hi> it has coſt, how many <hi>Innocents</hi> it has maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacred, how many <hi>ſtrong men have been ſlain by it;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 7.26.</note> what <hi>Havock</hi> it has made in <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>illuſtrious</hi> Families, and what <hi>Confuſion</hi> in the <hi>Race</hi> of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The laſt Argument I ſhall name of the greatneſs of this Sin, is the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which God, whoſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are always righteous, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver exceed the meaſure of our Iniquities, hath allotted for it. And this makes another very dreadfull <hi>Scene.</hi> There is Infamy, Hatred, Pain, and Poverty coming on <hi>like an armed Man;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 6.24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> then a <hi>diſmal Train</hi> of cruel, noiſom, and fierce Diſeaſes, followed cloſe by the ghaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151439:14"/>
                     <hi>King of Terrors</hi> in a ſorrowfull and <hi>untimely</hi> hour; All gathering about <hi>the Criminal,</hi> till the latter having pierct <hi>his Liver</hi> with a poyſon'd <hi>Dart,</hi> ſeizes and carries him off to God's <hi>high Tribunal;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 7.23.</note> the mean while <hi>the Heavens</hi> ſhew their Diſpleaſure in terrible <hi>Flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> of Divine Wrath upon the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the <hi>Sinner,</hi> who had been often told <hi>from thence</hi> (but perhaps till his dying Day, and his uneaſie Pillow forc'd <hi>the unwelcome thought</hi> upon him, never laid it to his heart) <hi>that no Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger,<note place="margin">Eph. 5.5.</note> nor unclean Perſon hath any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in the Kingdom of Chriſt, and of God.</hi> The <hi>Air</hi> of that <hi>holy place</hi> is infinitely too pure for him, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation too <hi>refined</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> the Company too <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>excellent</hi> to admit ſo <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>corrupt</hi> a Member into their Bleſſed Society. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch men are every way apt to <hi>turn the Grace of God into wantonneſs,</hi> and to argue from it, that for <hi>ſhort Pleaſures</hi> he will not exclude them from <hi>eternal Joys,</hi> and much leſs inflict <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Torments</hi> upon them; he has given them fair warning to expect that he will be true to his Threatnings. <hi>Be not deceived</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151439:14"/>Fornicators, nor Adulterers, nor Effeminate, ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. But ſtill there is a much ſadder <hi>Doom</hi> behind, the <hi>Terrour</hi> of which is beyond all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. where <hi>Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers</hi> (with other very bad Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) are ſentenc'd to <hi>the Lake that burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with Fire and Brimſtone,</hi> the fier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt Emblem of Divine Indignation, for ever and ever; and <hi>who can dwell with everlaſting Burnings!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus I have prov'd, that the <hi>Viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Conjugal Union is <hi>a great Wickedneſs,</hi> which was <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it: And the Reſult of what hath been ſpoken is, that whoſoever indulgeth himſelf in ſo vile a Practice, renounceth the Principles of <hi>natural,</hi> as well as <hi>revealed</hi> Religion, and is an utter Apoſtate from <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> For, in good earneſt, what is <hi>he,</hi> who to gratifie the Paſſion of a <hi>Goat,</hi> deflowers the <hi>Image,</hi> and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> of his Maker? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>files his <hi>Temple,</hi> and cares not what <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Miſchief</hi> he brings upon his honeſt and inoffenſive <hi>Neighbour?</hi> who is guilty of the <hi>fouleſt Treachery</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, tempting his Wife out of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151439:15"/>his Boſom to commit <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 2.17.</note> to break her moſt <hi>ſacred Vows,</hi> to forſake the <hi>Guide of her Youth,</hi> and renounce <hi>the Covenant of her God?</hi> To be the <hi>Plague</hi> and <hi>Ruin</hi> of her Family, to endure the utmoſt <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Scorn</hi> of Men, and for a few <hi>Moments</hi> of <hi>falſe</hi> Pleaſure to be <hi>eternally damn'd?</hi> who is a <hi>common Enemy</hi> to Mankind, who defies the <hi>impartial</hi> Juſtice of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and <hi>breaks through</hi> all the Fences of <hi>Modeſty, Religion,</hi> and <hi>the Fear of Hell,</hi> to <hi>ſteal</hi> a forbidden Pleaſure, and to <hi>raviſh</hi> an infamous and impure <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment?</hi> If this be a Man of <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> 'tis time to caſhier the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions of <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil;</hi> After this let all <hi>Contradictions</hi> be reconciled; let <hi>Light</hi> be cloathed with <hi>Sables,</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> put on the <hi>Brightneſs</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renity</hi> of the Day; let there be no more diſpute about the <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Merit</hi> of Actions, but let all things be juſt, as every mans Fancy or Humour <hi>paints</hi> them.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Rejoyce, O young Man in thy Youth, and let thy Heart chear thee in the days of thy Youth, and walk in the ways of thy Heart, and in the ſight of thine Eyes. But</hi> pauſe a little, and <hi>know thou, that for all theſe things,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151439:15"/>God will bring thee into Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I proceed now to the ſecond Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. The uſe which <hi>Joſeph</hi> made of this <hi>Thought</hi> upon the rude Aſſault of his Maſter's Wife. By the <hi>Impulſe</hi> of it he immediately daſht the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and reſcued his Innocence with this pious Anſwer, <hi>How can I do this great Wickedneſs?</hi> &amp;c. which came very <hi>naturally</hi> from one that had been bleſt with a <hi>virtuous Education,</hi> that was brought up in the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and deſcended (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> was) from the <hi>beſt-ordered</hi> and the <hi>moſt religious</hi> Family upon Earth; whoſe <hi>great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtor</hi> was dignified with the character of the <hi>Friend of God,</hi> and of one that <hi>would command his Children and his houſhold after him,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.19.</note> that they ſhould keep the way of the Lord, to do Juſtice and Judgment. Jacob</hi> alſo had frequent En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe with God,<note place="margin">Gen. 37.3.</note> and <hi>Joſeph</hi> being his Father's <hi>Darling,</hi> there is no doubt but he took particular care to <hi>adorn</hi> and <hi>enrich</hi> his M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd with <hi>good Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> as he had done to cloath him with <hi>coſtly</hi> and <hi>invidious</hi> Raiment. And this was it that preſerv'd his <hi>Innocence,</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151439:16"/>upheld his <hi>Integrity,</hi> and laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all his <hi>Greatneſs</hi> in <hi>Egypt:</hi> It was the <hi>Fear of God</hi> timely and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually <hi>inſtill'd</hi> into him by his religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Parent, which made him inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all Temptations, even in his <hi>boyling</hi> Youth, and amidſt the moſt <hi>inflaming</hi> and <hi>importuning</hi> Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And from hence we gain the following Inſtructions.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the ſtrongeſt Temptations to the moſt flattering and deceitfull Vices are not invincible. There is no Age of the Life of Man ſo eager of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Pleaſures, or ſo little acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the <hi>Fallacies</hi> of them, as <hi>Youth.</hi> And if <hi>frail Youth,</hi> when ſo highly tempted <hi>can</hi> refuſe to ſin, and is able to withſtand the Charms and Allurements of <hi>Female</hi> Courtſhip; if a Hebrew Servant can deſpiſe the <hi>Flames</hi> of an <hi>Egyptian</hi> Lady, was not caught by her <hi>treacherous Wiles,</hi> nor bended by her <hi>Commands,</hi> neither by her <hi>ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> nor <hi>imperious</hi> Looks; was not vanquiſht by her <hi>repeated Importunities,</hi> nor awed by the Fears of her <hi>Revenge,</hi> nor inveigl'd by the hopes of <hi>Secrecy,</hi> nor ſoften'd by the <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor betray'd by the <hi>Frailties</hi> of Fleſh
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151439:16"/>and Blood; then ſurely are all the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> of Vice <hi>reſiſtible,</hi> and there is no Danger of any <hi>Compulſion</hi> to be wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. If <hi>Joſeph</hi> refuſed the moſt <hi>flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> Pleaſures, and <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>Royal</hi> Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Delights of the Court of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, chuſing rather to ſuffer Affliction with the people of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> 
                     <hi>than enjoy the pleaſures of ſin for a ſeaſon;</hi> No man in the like circumſtances can have any reaſon to complain that he lies under a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of ſinning. For let the man that would fain diſcharge his ſins upon the <hi>Fatality</hi> of humane Actions conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with himſelf, whether he has not the <hi>ſame Faculties</hi> which other men have; the ſame power of <hi>chuſing</hi> and <hi>refuſing</hi> what is <hi>fit</hi> and <hi>unfit</hi> to be done, of weighing the <hi>Arguments</hi> on both ſides, and determining on that which beſt recommends it ſelf to his <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judgment:</hi> And what it is that hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him from being as <hi>ſtanch</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> againſt a wicked Cuſtom or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as thoſe whom the <hi>ſame</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments which lie before him have prevailed upon, and the <hi>excellent Men</hi> of all Ages have ever been. If he thinks that all Mankind are determined by a rigid and irreſiſtible <hi>Fate,</hi> to do all the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151439:17"/>
                     <hi>evil</hi> that has been done in the world, let in reconcile his opinion, if he can, to the <hi>general Senſe</hi> and <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of Mankind, who are conſcious of nothing more than a <hi>Freedom of Choice</hi> and <hi>Action,</hi> and find it <hi>natural</hi> to chide and accuſe themſelves for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting contrary to the Dictates of their own <hi>reaſon,</hi> and the holy <hi>Oracles</hi> of God; inſomuch, that if they had the <hi>higheſt Freedom</hi> imaginable, they could not have greater Aſſurance of it, than they now have of that <hi>degree</hi> of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which is commonly aſcribed to them, and every <hi>penitent Sinner</hi> is an undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Witneſs</hi> and <hi>Confeſſor</hi> of. And here I would ask the <hi>Fataliſt</hi> a fair que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion or two.</p>
                  <p>As firſt, what greater Evidence can there be of a <hi>free Agent</hi> in any crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Caſe, than his <hi>pleading guilty</hi> to the Indictments of his own <hi>Conſcience?</hi> Secondly, What better Argument than this, can he or any other <hi>Fataliſt</hi> bring to prove the contrary? And then Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I would only ask him, How he knows himſelf to be a <hi>neceſſary Agent,</hi> ſince no other Agents of <hi>this kind</hi> have any <hi>Knowledge</hi> of the Principles they are acted by? And 'tis certain, they have
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151439:17"/>no uſe of any ſuch knowledge, being wholly moved and determined by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal</hi> Cauſes and Objects, or ſome <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inſtinct,</hi> whoſe Powers they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſpute, or fail of their obedience to; and yet as truly ſerve the <hi>end</hi> of their Beings, as if they had all the Perfections of an <hi>Angel</hi> to diſpoſe them to it.</p>
                  <p>And the like anſwer may be given to the Plea of <hi>humane Frailty,</hi> as it is frequently urged to leſſen the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> and to magnifie the <hi>power of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations</hi> above the <hi>ſtated</hi> Meaſures and Attainments of it; <hi>viz.</hi> that it contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts the experience of all the <hi>great Examples</hi> of Virtue and Piety, and the Confeſſions of penitent and <hi>ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convicted</hi> Sinners, who when they are <hi>moſt ſenſible</hi> of the Frailties of humane Nature, and are <hi>themſelves</hi> ſome of the <hi>ſaddeſt Inſtances</hi> of them, do hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily <hi>bewail</hi> their eaſie Compliances, and <hi>ſcore</hi> their Miſcarriages upon their <hi>own Folly</hi> and <hi>Wickedneſs.</hi> 'Tis indeed a common (and in ſome mens eſteem a very <hi>plauſible</hi>) excuſe to ſay, <hi>It was ill done; but what Fleſh could withſtand ſuch Temptations? The greateſt Virtue muſt have ſubmitted to them:</hi> But how
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151439:18"/>do they know this, that have ſo <hi>little Virtue</hi> as to libel <hi>the Grace of God,</hi> and the <hi>Integrity</hi> of all good Men, who have ſtood their ground, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd their <hi>Innocence</hi> againſt the moſt <hi>violent Guſts</hi> of Temptation, and the <hi>fierceſt Aſſaults</hi> of Hell? The World is not ignorant, that there have been Perſons of <hi>eminent</hi> Goodneſs and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in all Ages of it; Men that have fill'd the <hi>Mouth of Fame</hi> with their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous and noble Actions, that have had the <hi>hardneſs</hi> to reſiſt the <hi>ſofteſt</hi> charms and the <hi>grimmeſt</hi> Terrours of <hi>Senſe,</hi> and have encountred all kinds of Temptation with <hi>good Succeſs,</hi> while they ſtood upon the <hi>ſame</hi> level, and were <hi>ſubject to like Paſſions</hi> and Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities with our ſelves. And ſince we have the <hi>ſame Aſſurances</hi> of Divine Grace and Aſſiſtence which they had, 'tis <hi>impious</hi> and infinitely <hi>vain</hi> to think of eaſing our <hi>guilty Minds,</hi> by throwing off the blame of our Impurities and Sins upon <hi>Fate,</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> or the <hi>Temptations</hi> which are <hi>common to Men,</hi> when nothing can make us <hi>Sinners</hi> but <hi>our ſelves.</hi> Infinite power <hi>it ſelf</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>compell</hi> us to a Fault; I mean, not only becauſe it is <hi>inſeparable</hi> from infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151439:18"/>
                     <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> but becauſe it is <hi>irreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible,</hi> and there can be <hi>no fault</hi> in yielding to <hi>a Force</hi> which there can be <hi>no poſſibility</hi> of reſiſting. And this will juſtifie the Dealings of God with the <hi>Deſpiſers</hi> of his <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> to all Eternity, that they have <hi>choſen</hi> their own ruin, and left him <hi>no way</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, but to put up their <hi>intolerable</hi> Contempt of his <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Sanctions,</hi> or break their <hi>ſpecifick Frame,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Freedom</hi> of their Wills, which is <hi>eſſential</hi> to all true Virtue and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. That it is a mighty advantage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the leading a <hi>virtuous</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted</hi> Life, and avoiding the <hi>great Gulphs</hi> of Vice and Wickedneſs, to be brought up in the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and to have our Minds (while they are <hi>green</hi> and <hi>tender</hi>) ſeaſon'd by a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Education. The <hi>Tenour</hi> of our Lives generally depends upon the <hi>firſt Principles</hi> that are planted in us, and the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> we begin in our Youth and Childhood; If they be <hi>good,</hi> there is nothing ſo <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>powerfull</hi> to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Decoys and Flatteries of Sin and Vice. And where <hi>ſuch</hi> Principles are not <hi>timely</hi> ſown and cheriſht, ſo as
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151439:19"/>to grow into ſome <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence,</hi> and be of ſome uſe and ſervice to us in our Youth (while Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Pleaſure and Vanity look <hi>freſh</hi> and <hi>gay,</hi> and the <hi>Snake</hi> hides it ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Flower</hi>) vicious Inclinations will certainly grow up in their <hi>room,</hi> and being more taking and natural to the <hi>depraved Soil,</hi> will mightily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the <hi>Culture</hi> and <hi>Improvement</hi> of it. And hence you may obſerve, as much as the faſhion is to Diſpute over all the Principles of <hi>revealed</hi> Religion, no man queſtions the <hi>Currency</hi> of ſuch Maxims as theſe, That the greateſt <hi>Errors</hi> both in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> are the unhappy <hi>Fruits</hi> of a <hi>careleſs</hi> or <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> Education; That Youth let looſe from the Reins of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> runs the <hi>wildeſt</hi> of any thing in the World; That good <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and <hi>Education</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to <hi>govern</hi> youthfull Paſſions, to manage <hi>wanton</hi> and <hi>unruly</hi> Nature, and keep it in <hi>the way it ſhould go;</hi> and that the effects of them are commonly ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>happy</hi> and <hi>durable;</hi> as the wiſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervator tells us,<note place="margin">Prov. 22.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go, and when he is old he will not depart from it.</hi> Having <hi>drank in</hi> the Principles of divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151439:19"/>his <hi>Eyes</hi> are ſuddenly inlightned; and being gradually exerciſed <hi>in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning between good and evil,</hi> he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſees through the <hi>Diſguiſes</hi> of Vice and Folly, and ſo eaſily evades the <hi>Deluſions</hi> of them.</p>
                  <p>And this was <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Happineſs, and a ſingular Advantage it was to him, when he came to live in a <hi>Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and to make a figure in a <hi>Court,</hi> where he had ſo much <hi>occaſion</hi> for it. Alas! what would the <hi>young man</hi> have done, had he been bred up in the <hi>Mode</hi> and <hi>Faſhion</hi> of our Age, to <hi>dreſs,</hi> and <hi>comb,</hi> and <hi>dance</hi> the <hi>round</hi> of Luxury and Vanity? To court the Daughters of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and Revenge the Rape of <hi>Dinah</hi> upon the Siſters of <hi>Sichem,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>ſparkiſh</hi> Pretences of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Honour?</hi> Had he learnt his Leſſon from the <hi>Stage,</hi> or the <hi>Schools</hi> of Scepticiſm and Profaneneſs, been taught to <hi>ſhrug</hi> and ſmile at the <hi>grave</hi> Precepts of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and call every thing <hi>ſilly</hi> that is <hi>ſerious,</hi> to defie the <hi>Threats</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to bury his <hi>Fears</hi> in Wine, and then <hi>make a mock at ſin,</hi> and a Jeſt at being <hi>damned?</hi> Had <hi>Joſeph</hi> been thus initiated in the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> he had certainly flown into the Tempters
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151439:20"/>Arms,<note place="margin">Prov. 7.23.</note> 
                     <hi>like a Bird</hi> (as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks in his caſe) <hi>that haſteth to the ſnare, and knoweth not that it is for his life.</hi> He would ſurely never have diſparaged his <hi>Breeding</hi> ſo much as to ſtagger at the <hi>greateſs</hi> of the Crime, or allow him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a moment to think of the <hi>fatal conſequence;</hi> but without Fear or Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight have followed his Leader to <hi>the Chambers of Death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 7.27.</note> in the Paths that <hi>go down to Hell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis true, that the <hi>choice</hi> of our Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation lies very little (if at all) in our <hi>own</hi> Power: but therefore it infinitely concerns thoſe into whoſe <hi>Arms</hi> (by the Providence of God) we are <hi>caſt</hi> in our Infancy, and on whom we are forc't to <hi>lean</hi> all the time of our <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Childhood,</hi> to principle our Minds with an <hi>early</hi> Senſe of God and Religion, to <hi>ſuperviſe</hi> our Actions, and <hi>rectifie</hi> our Errors, and as it were lead us <hi>by the hand</hi> through the <hi>firſt</hi> Stages of Virtue and Piety, till we are paſt the <hi>mighty Dangers</hi> of Youth, and in ſome meaſure able to grapple with the Temptations of <hi>Senſe,</hi> and ſecure our ſelves againſt the Fallacies and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of the <hi>Devil.</hi> This, we all know, is the immediate and indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151439:20"/>Duty of <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Guardians,</hi> the neglect of which hath ruin'd <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious</hi> Numbers of <hi>ignorant</hi> Souls, yea thouſands of the <hi>braveſt</hi> of our Youth, who might have proved the Strength and Ornaments of our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> had they begun at the <hi>beginning of Wiſdom,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 9.10.</note> been timely train'd up in the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> and carefully taught to <hi>approve the things that are excellent.</hi> If therefore you deſire to ſee your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren happy, live virtuouſly, and <hi>eſcape the Pollutions which are in the world through Luſt;</hi> If you would not leave an <hi>accurſed Brood</hi> behind you, to waſt your Eſtates with <hi>riotous living,</hi> and curſe you when you are gone, and <hi>to your Faces,</hi> when they meet you at <hi>God's Tribunal;</hi> let your care of them appear, by teaching them betimes <hi>whom they ſhould fear,</hi> that when they are attackt by any Temptation, they may be able (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did) to reaſon themſelves into a <hi>Victory</hi> over it; which leads to the third and laſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction:</p>
                  <p n="3">III. That the Fear of God quickned with a <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>lively</hi> Apprehenſion of the <hi>great evil</hi> of Sin, is a ſovereign
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151439:21"/>and effectual <hi>Preſervative</hi> againſt the moſt <hi>charming</hi> and <hi>powerfull</hi> Allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to it. 'Tis the Nature of Fear to lay a Reſtraint upon the Mind, while it views the <hi>Danger</hi> that lies before it: and ſince the greateſt Danger lies in provoking infinite Juſtice <hi>arm'd</hi> with infinite Power, the Fear of God who is inveſted with <hi>both,</hi> and has threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Sinner with everlaſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, muſt, while he is under the lively Impreſſions of it, <hi>deaden</hi> all the force of Temptations, and infallibly reſtrain him from cloſing with them. And for this reaſon it is, that God, who is infinitely tender of our immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Souls,<note place="margin">Rom 1.18</note> hath <hi>revealed his Wrath from Heaven againſt all ungodlineſs and unrighteouſneſs of Men,</hi> and kindly <hi>threatned</hi> Deſtruction on purpoſe to preſerve us from it; it being greatly to be feared, that the Promiſe of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and <hi>everlaſting Life</hi> would very hardly have made the <hi>beſt</hi> Men <hi>good,</hi> if they had not been alſo <hi>quickned</hi> with the Fears of <hi>everlaſting Perdition.</hi> For 'tis certain, that in this <hi>guilty</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate</hi> State we are generally much more <hi>afraid</hi> of being miſerable, than <hi>ambitious</hi> to be truly happy. Of which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151439:21"/>I think there needs no plainer Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration than this, <hi>viz.</hi> that the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality</hi> of Men, even when they are grown <hi>weary</hi> of this World, would be well <hi>contented</hi> to ſtay here in a tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition to <hi>Eternity,</hi> or when they die to <hi>vaniſh</hi> into nothing, <hi>only</hi> to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the <hi>danger</hi> of being <hi>everlaſtingly miſerable.</hi> Nay, I doubt not but ſome <hi>good men</hi> of the <hi>lower Size</hi> in Religion, that have but a moderate ſhare of the Sorrows and Calamities of this Life, would be (were it left to their choice) almoſt willing to reſign their <hi>weak Hopes</hi> of Heaven, for ſuch infallible Securities againſt the <hi>dreadfull</hi> and eternal Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Hell. And ſince the <hi>fear</hi> of endleſs Miſery has taken ſo <hi>deep a root</hi> in humane Nature, were our Minds duely <hi>Impregnated</hi> and kept awake with the <hi>Fear of God,</hi> who <hi>is</hi> both <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſave and deſtroy,</hi> it is <hi>morally</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, but that it muſt <hi>prevail</hi> over all Temptations to incurr his Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and effectually <hi>curb</hi> our <hi>wildeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>unruly</hi> Inclinations to any Luſt or Vanity. And hence is that excellent ſaying of the Wife-man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.14.<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Happy is the Man that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth elways,</hi> i.e. that hath <hi>the Fear of God</hi> continually <hi>before his Eyes,</hi> as a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151439:22"/>faithfull <hi>Watch</hi> or <hi>Sentinel</hi> to diſcover all Approaches of <hi>Danger,</hi> and call in the <hi>Powers</hi> of Reaſon and Religion to his Defence againſt them.</p>
                  <p>No Motive indeed, tho' never ſo <hi>powerfull</hi> in it ſelf, has any <hi>force</hi> upon us any longer than we apprehend our Concernment in it; for which Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon an <hi>actual Apprehenſion</hi> of the <hi>evil</hi> of the Crime to which we are tempted, is abſolutely neceſſary to reſtrain us from it, by <hi>awakening</hi> the Fear of God in our Minds. And therefore when any Temptation is preſented to us, if we look only on the <hi>gloſſie ſide</hi> of it, and think of nothing but the delicious <hi>Pleaſure</hi> or <hi>Profit</hi> the Sin is <hi>varniſht</hi> or <hi>gilded</hi> with, and are not aware the mean while, that God has <hi>revealed his Wrath</hi> againſt it, 'tis evident that what ever we are at other times, we are not <hi>now</hi> afraid of offending him; and then <hi>his Fear</hi> can have no <hi>preſent effect</hi> upon us, and ſo it is all one in the Iſſue, as if we never had any true Reverence for him.</p>
                  <p>And this was it that made the great Difference between <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>David</hi> in the matter we have been treating of. <hi>David</hi> had an <hi>habitual Fear</hi> of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151439:22"/>God, and ſurely in as high a Degree as <hi>Joſeph</hi> had: But then there was this Diſparity in <hi>his</hi> Caſe, the Fear of God was not <hi>before his Eyes</hi> when he <hi>bath'd</hi> them in the naked Beauty of <hi>unguard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bathſheba;</hi> he did not, like <hi>Joſeph,</hi> awaken himſelf into a <hi>vigorous</hi> Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>great Wickedneſs</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi>'s Bed. He never argued thus to himſelf, How can I harbour ſo <hi>impure</hi> a Thought, and ſtain my <hi>Royal Purple</hi> with ſo <hi>foul</hi> and Action, a <hi>Sin</hi> of a far <hi>deeper Dye?</hi> Shall I thus <hi>offend?</hi> Thus <hi>requite</hi> the good and mighty God, who chang'd my home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Crook</hi> into a glorious <hi>Scepter,</hi> and advanced me (the youngeſt of <hi>Jeſſe</hi>'s Houſe) over all the Sons of <hi>rejected Saul,</hi> to the higheſt ſtep of <hi>Imperial Honour,</hi> next to <hi>himſelf</hi> in Power and Dignity, and from <hi>thoſe few ſheep</hi> I kept <hi>in the Wilderneſs,</hi> has made me Ruler over his <hi>beloved</hi> Iſrael? <hi>Shall</hi> I thus <hi>provoke the Lord to Anger?</hi> Am I <hi>ſtronger than he?</hi> Had <hi>David</hi> thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken'd himſelf into an holy Awe of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>his Goodneſs,</hi> he had ſurely beat off the Temptation that ſo eaſily <hi>foil'd</hi> him, been innocent of <hi>both</hi> his <hi>preſumptuous Sins,</hi> and perfectly clear
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151439:23"/>in the whole <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now, having given you the true <hi>Character</hi> of Adultery, and the <hi>Inſtructions</hi> left you by the <hi>young</hi> and <hi>pious</hi> Example in the Text, I ſhall cloſe all with a brief Application to two ſorts of Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To ſuch as are burden'd with the guilt of this heinous Crime: who are to be admoniſht, that a Sin of ſo <hi>vaſt Malignity</hi> requires a very <hi>ſolemn piercing</hi> and <hi>unfeigned</hi> Repentance; and that the <hi>conſcious</hi> Eye and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial</hi> Juſtice of God are not to be <hi>deceived</hi> by any <hi>Forms</hi> or <hi>Flaſhes</hi> of a <hi>tranſient</hi> and <hi>impenitent</hi> Sorrow. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider then, yours is a <hi>crying</hi> Sin; To <hi>Heaven</hi> it cries for <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and to <hi>you</hi> it calls <hi>aloud</hi> for the deepeſt <hi>Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation in Duſt and Aſhes,</hi> the greateſt <hi>Contrition</hi> of Mind and Spirit, the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Satisfaction</hi> in your power to the injured Parties, the freeſt and moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing <hi>Confeſſions</hi> to Almighty God, the ſincereſt <hi>Vows</hi> and Reſolutions of a <hi>new</hi> and <hi>unſpotted</hi> Life, the ſtricteſt <hi>Covenant with your Eyes,</hi> the ſtrongeſt <hi>Guard</hi> upon all the <hi>Avenues</hi> of Luſt and Wantonneſs, and the <hi>niceſt Care</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void the very leaſt <hi>Pollutions</hi> of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151439:23"/>
                     <hi>Fleſh</hi> or <hi>Spirit,</hi> together with a moſt paſſionate endeavour to reſcue the <hi>poor Captives</hi> that are tied and bound with the <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>your Sins,</hi> and were by you betrayed into the <hi>Snare of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</hi> What <hi>Rivers of Tears</hi> can waſh away ſo <hi>deep</hi> a Stain? What <hi>Piercings</hi> of <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Soul?</hi> What Self-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and Abhorrence? What <hi>lively</hi> Applications to the Merits of your <hi>Redeemer</hi> ought to accompany your <hi>fervent</hi> and <hi>conſtant Prayers</hi> for the Forgiveneſs of ſo <hi>great a Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?</hi> A Wickedneſs <hi>ſo great,</hi> that the greateſt <hi>Purity of Life</hi> is little enough to take off the <hi>Blemiſh</hi> of one <hi>ſingle</hi> Act of it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.12.</note> and reſtore the Joys of <hi>that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Hope</hi> of being <hi>meet</hi> at laſt <hi>for the glorious Inheritance of the Saints in Light.</hi> And then, into what a <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Condition hath that man brought himſelf, that has a <hi>long courſe</hi> of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications and Adulteries to anſwer for, and is ſtill to begin the whole <hi>Chriſtian Race?</hi> He had need, I am ſure to live the <hi>reverſe</hi> of his Life apace; I mean, to ſpend the remainder in continual Acts of <hi>Mortification, Devotion,</hi> and <hi>Preparation</hi> for his <hi>dying</hi> hour; in <hi>unra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling</hi> (as far as he is able) all the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151439:24"/>
                     <hi>evil</hi> he has done, and doing all the <hi>good,</hi> which the <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Patience</hi> of God, his ſhort time, and <hi>unhappy</hi> Circumſtances may have left him op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for. 'Tis certain that God has pardon'd ſome very <hi>great</hi> and <hi>infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Sinners; but then they were <hi>great Penitents</hi> too. And ſurely there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more <hi>becoming</hi> ſuch as have been very <hi>bad</hi> themſelves, than to attempt ſome <hi>generous</hi> and <hi>eminent</hi> thing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Reformation of a <hi>degenerate</hi> and <hi>adulterous</hi> Age; ſomething that may heal the Honour of <hi>Virtue,</hi> that may help to appeaſe the <hi>Anger of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and to baniſh the <hi>Vices</hi> which they, their Families, and Country have dearly ſmarted for; that the World may be once <hi>the better</hi> for them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they leave it, and their <hi>good</hi> Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons may help to bury the <hi>Memory</hi> and <hi>I fection</hi> of their <hi>bad.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Such as have not defiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with <hi>carnal</hi> Luſts, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly thoſe that are <hi>young</hi> and <hi>tender</hi> of the <hi>Honour</hi> they owe their <hi>Bodies,</hi> or are curious in their <hi>Waſhes</hi> and <hi>Dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and love to appear <hi>orient</hi> and <hi>gay,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>Spot</hi> of Soil or Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ought to be extremely cautious
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151439:24"/>of all <hi>Approaches</hi> to this notoriouſly <hi>ſhamefull</hi> and <hi>odious</hi> Vice.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.18.</note> Other Sins <hi>comparatively</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>are without the Body; but he that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth Fornication, ſinneth againſt his own Body,</hi> i.e. he <hi>deflowers</hi> the <hi>Purity</hi> of his excellent Nature, he commits a <hi>Rape</hi> upon <hi>himſelf,</hi> and ſo <hi>defiles</hi> his holy Profeſſion,<note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 4.4.</note> which is to preſerve his <hi>Body</hi> (as a ſacred <hi>Veſſel</hi>) in <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> and to <hi>keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unſpotted from the World.</hi> And then what <hi>fooliſh</hi> and <hi>fulſome</hi> Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie were it, to pretend to the <hi>minuteſt Decencies,</hi> and profeſs the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of <hi>Nuptial Sanctity,</hi> and after all contract the <hi>indelible Stain,</hi> and perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly embrace ſuch a <hi>Dunghill</hi> Luſt? Take heed therefore of every <hi>impure</hi> and <hi>guilty</hi> Thought, of all <hi>unchaſt</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Complacences, <hi>laſcivious</hi> Glances and Dalliances, of all <hi>Immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> in Word or Geſture, with all other Incentives to gratifie <hi>the Fleſh with its Affections and Luſts.</hi> Theſe, beſides their <hi>proper</hi> Guilt and Defilement, are the common <hi>Anteludes</hi> by which the <hi>ſly</hi> Tempter ſeeks to play you into the <hi>dreadfull Crime:</hi> and then by ſhunning the Occaſions of them you keep out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151439:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151439:25"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151439:26"/>of the road (at leaſt) of <hi>vulgar</hi> Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, in the <hi>pure Aethereal</hi> way, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>unclean Spirit</hi> never or rarely preſumes to come. But ſuppoſe you were ſurprized by a rude and violent Temptation (as <hi>Joſeph</hi> or ſad <hi>Lucretia</hi> was) <hi>Luſts</hi> fiery Darts will not enter into a <hi>chaſt</hi> and <hi>undefiled</hi> Breaſt, where there is nothing <hi>groſs</hi> enough to catch or feed the Flame.<note place="margin">Prov. 4.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Keep therefore thy Heart with all Diligence;</hi> and if thine Eye chance to be ſtruck with <hi>ſtrange erratick</hi> Beauty, call in the mighty powers of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> arm your ſelf with a <hi>Reverence</hi> of God's all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye,<note place="margin">Pſ. 139.3.</note> which pierceth into all <hi>your Paths,</hi> and is ever <hi>about your Bed;</hi> call to mind your infinite Obligations to him, and look on every <hi>Inſtigation</hi> of luſtfull Appetite, as a dangerous Approach to the <hi>flaming</hi> borders of <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Ruin,</hi> where the <hi>Worm</hi> of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>dieth not, and the Fire</hi> of Divine Wrath <hi>is not quenched.</hi> Say now to thy ſelf, <hi>How can I do</hi> ſo <hi>falſe,</hi> ſo <hi>foul</hi> an Action, that have <hi>plighted my Faith,</hi> and eſpouſed my ſelf by moſt ſolemn and religious Vows, <hi>as a chaſt Virgin unto Chriſt,</hi> as a <hi>Lover</hi> of the pureſt and holieſt <hi>Jeſus?</hi> How can I hope to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151439:26"/>appear before him amongſt thoſe <hi>bright</hi> and <hi>ſpotleſs</hi> Souls,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.33.</note> that have <hi>eſcaped the Pollutions that are in the World through Luſt?</hi> May he not juſtly ſet me with the <hi>Goats on his left hand,</hi> in the great <hi>diſcriminating</hi> Day, if here I ſhould live like them in <hi>turpid</hi> and <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> Pleaſures? Should I ſtoop to this <hi>lewd</hi> Deſire, <hi>Whither, oh whither ſhall I cauſe my ſhame to go?</hi> How ſhall I behold the Face of God or Angels? Is this to <hi>purifie my ſelf as they are pure?</hi> Shall I <hi>then</hi> for a <hi>moments</hi> Pleaſure for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit an <hi>immortal</hi> Crown, and incur the <hi>eternal</hi> Anger of him whom at laſt I <hi>muſt obey,</hi> when he bids me <hi>depart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting Fire?</hi> Shall I ſhew leſs reaſon in my Conduct, be more <hi>bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh than any Man,</hi> and run directly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Rock</hi> by whoſe <hi>fatal ſide</hi> I have lately ſeen the <hi>Ruins</hi> of ſo many <hi>tall</hi> and <hi>gallant</hi> Veſſels, ſo many <hi>brave</hi> and <hi>goodly</hi> Perſons, fearleſs and undaunted Men, with <hi>deſperate</hi> Numbers of the <hi>ſmaller Craft,</hi> miſerably <hi>loſt</hi> and <hi>caſt away</hi> for ever? And for thoſe few <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers</hi> that have hardly eſcapt with <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Limb,</hi> how have I ſeen them <hi>ſtalking</hi> about the Streets <hi>like Ghoſts,</hi> with <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>ſtrange Remorſe</hi> in their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151439:27"/>Faces? Only more chang'd from what they were, than Death uſually alters a man from his <hi>living Form?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will ſay but one thing more; you have <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> before you; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the various Iſſues of a <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>fooliſh</hi> Choice, declared by the <hi>everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Goſpel,</hi> which forbids you no inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Pleaſure.<note place="margin">Rom 8.13.</note> 
                     <hi>If you live after the Fleſh, you ſhall die: but if through the Spirit you mortifie the Deeds of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, you ſhall live,</hi> in raviſhing and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Joys, in eternal Acts of unſpotted and <hi>Seraphick</hi> Love, in the Arms of him that loved you to the <hi>Death,</hi> in the <hi>Beatific</hi> Viſion and Fruition of God, and the deareſt Embraces of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Spirits made perfect in Heaven.</hi> To which God of his infinite Mercy guide us through the Snares and Fallacies of this evil World, for the Merits of his Bleſſed Son <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151439:27"/>
                  <head>A SERMON ON THE <hi>Chriſtian Warfare.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>S. James IV. 7.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>— Reſiſt the Devil, and he will flee from you.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>'TIs a peculiar Thought of a late conceited Philoſopher, who loved to quarrel with the <hi>beſt ſenſe</hi> of Mankind, <hi>that War is founded in Nature;</hi> or a <hi>Right</hi> (as he calls it) in every man, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his <hi>power,</hi> to ſeize on every Mans <hi>Poſſeſſions,</hi> till he gives it away <hi>by Compact.</hi> The plain and naked Meaning of which Aſſertion is, That <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> are but one and the ſame thing <hi>in Nature;</hi> That all <hi>the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:151439:28"/>between them ariſes from <hi>poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Laws</hi> and <hi>Covenants;</hi> That till ſuch Laws and Covenants were made, no man was bound to his <hi>good Behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> to his Neighbour; that to <hi>oppreſs, raviſh,</hi> and <hi>murther,</hi> were once <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>innocent</hi> Actions, the harmleſs Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of <hi>Power,</hi> purſuant to that <hi>origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Right,</hi> which <hi>fond</hi> Nature gave the <hi>ſtronger</hi> to all the Delights and Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions of the <hi>weaker.</hi> But not to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the <hi>Chace</hi> of this <hi>wild</hi> and <hi>impious</hi> Hypotheſis, we need go no farther than the Text to diſcover the great <hi>Incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary of War</hi> and <hi>Contention,</hi> and the <hi>firſt Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Author</hi> of all Diſorder and Confuſion in the World; that is, <hi>the Devil,</hi> the common and inveterate Enemy of God, and every Creature that bears his <hi>Image.</hi> Him therefore S. <hi>James</hi> exhorts us to <hi>reſiſt;</hi> and leaſt we ſhould be daunted at the <hi>Fame</hi> of his mighty <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> and the vaſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions</hi> he hath every where <hi>wrought in the Earth,</hi> to ſupport us under this Diſcouragement, <hi>the Divine Herald</hi> aſſures us, that the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts with him will be ſafe and <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable;</hi> that <hi>Victory</hi> ſhall always at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend <hi>our Arms,</hi> and the <hi>Flight</hi> of our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151439:28"/>Enemy <hi>adorn</hi> our Triumph. <hi>Reſiſt the Devil and he will flee from you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe Words deſerve a very ſerious <hi>Conſultation</hi> with our ſelves about them; eſpecially when we <hi>firſt</hi> enter into <hi>the Chriſtian Warfare,</hi> or when-ever we are <hi>allarmed</hi> by any <hi>violent</hi> Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or are likely to be engag'd in any <hi>ſharp</hi> encounter with our <hi>Spiritual Adverſary.</hi> No wiſe Man begins a <hi>War</hi> without conſidering <hi>who,</hi> and <hi>how power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> his Enemy is; what <hi>play</hi> he is like to have from him, and what <hi>Force</hi> he is able to advance againſt him; at leaſt, if it be a <hi>War</hi> (as the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is) that will ſurely hold him <hi>in breath</hi> till he has breath'd his very <hi>laſt</hi> in this world. And this Wiſdom <hi>our Saviour</hi> teaches his Followers, as a common inſtance of <hi>military Prudence,</hi> Luke 14.31. <hi>For what King going to make war againſt another King, ſitteth not down firſt, and conſulteth whether he be able with ten thouſand to meet him that cometh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with twenty thouſand?</hi> where we ſee, the neceſſary points to be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved before we enter into the <hi>Field</hi> of <hi>Action</hi> are, <hi>What Forces</hi> our Enemy is provided with, and <hi>what power</hi> we have to make good our <hi>Defence</hi> againſt him.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151439:29"/>And ſince it is evident by our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s <hi>Argument,</hi> that the ſucceſs of our <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Warfare</hi> depends upon the right and timely Reſolution of theſe <hi>weighty</hi> Queſtions, and a competent Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them is apparently <hi>neceſſary</hi> to ſuch a Reſolution, to make this Diſcourſe the more clear and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, I ſhall diſtinctly conſider theſe three Particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. The <hi>Strength</hi> of our Enemy, and wherein his great <hi>Power</hi> to hurt us lies.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. What Power we have to <hi>reſiſt</hi> him, or by what means we may effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually guard and ſecure our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. What Aſſurance we have, that <hi>the Devil</hi> will yield to our Reſiſtance, and <hi>flee from us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">I. The <hi>Strength</hi> of our Enemy, and wherein his <hi>great Power</hi> to hurt us lies. The <hi>Fall</hi> of the Apoſtate Angels from Heaven, has (by Divine Permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) fill'd this <hi>lower World</hi> with innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable <hi>envious</hi> and <hi>malicious</hi> Spirits, under one <hi>Sovereign</hi> Prince or Leader,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151439:29"/>whom the Scripture commonly calls <hi>the Devil</hi> or <hi>Satan.</hi> This is that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> Spirit, who <hi>firſt</hi> (of his own wicked Motion) raiſed Rebellion in the calm and peacefull Regions of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Paradice,</hi> and has ever ſince made it his buſineſs to ſeduce and deſtroy the <hi>Worſhippers of God,</hi> to draw the World to his <hi>own Altars</hi> and <hi>Oracles,</hi> and to put <hi>all the Foundations of the Earth out of Courſe.</hi> It is not at all improbable, that <hi>he</hi> beguiled our Firſt Parents by appearing in the ſhape of a <hi>Seraph or flaming Serpent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Numb. 21.6</note> in which they had ſeen the <hi>Heavenly</hi> Seraphim attending the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> when God was pleas'd to <hi>ſhade</hi> himſelf <hi>with viſible Glory,</hi> and condeſcended to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with <hi>Man.</hi> And tho' we know not the Devil's <hi>particular Station</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>Fall,</hi> yet an Angel of ſome <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Order</hi> in the celeſtial <hi>Hierachy</hi> we may certainly conclude he had been, from his <hi>ancient Supremacy</hi> over the Spirits of his <hi>own Kingdom,</hi> and the great and eminent <hi>Titles</hi> by which <hi>he</hi> is frequently diſtinguiſtt <hi>in Scripture</hi> from them;<note place="margin">Matth 9.34.</note> ſuch as <hi>the Prince of the Devils,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 12.31.2 Cor. 4.4. Epheſ. 2.2.</note> the <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>God of this World,</hi> and <hi>the Prince of the Power of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151439:30"/>the Air;</hi> the latter of which denotes alſo <hi>the place</hi> of his Habitation, or <hi>the Camp</hi> where his great Armies meet, and receive his Orders to <hi>deceive the Nations,</hi> and enlarge his Kingdom o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this inferiour Orb. But whatever <hi>his place,</hi> or whatever his <hi>Crime</hi> in Heaven was, no ſooner was he driven thence into the Regions of the Air, but like <hi>the Firſt-born of the Children of Pride and Malice,</hi> he prepares to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> his Fall upon the <hi>Favourite</hi> of the <hi>new Creation.</hi> And obſerving Man, the Off-ſpring of <hi>Duſt</hi> and <hi>Clay,</hi> curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly wrought into a Creature of <hi>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing Form,</hi> dignified with the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage</hi> of God, and a <hi>Majeſtick Awe</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> over all below him, <hi>he</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently began to <hi>envy</hi> and <hi>moleſt</hi> his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and (which is all the happineſs he hath reſerved to himſelf) to conſpire and procure his Ruin.</p>
                  <p>To carry on this <hi>deſign</hi> the Devil has vaſt <hi>Legions</hi> of <hi>deſperate</hi> Spirits conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually at his Beck and Pleaſure; <hi>All</hi> delighting in the ſame Employment, <hi>all</hi> of them <hi>fired</hi> with the ſame Revenge, and involved in the ſame irreverſible Doom; <hi>all</hi> immortal and unbodied Spirits, and therefore <hi>ſuperiour</hi> to our
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151439:30"/>frail humane Nature, which is but Spirit <hi>mingled</hi> and <hi>allayed</hi> with Fleſh and Blood; and by the weak Contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its <hi>unequal</hi> Principles, and the <hi>affinity</hi> of our Bodies to the Elements of this World, is liable to the <hi>Fallacies</hi> and <hi>Diſtractions</hi> of ſenſual Objects, and ſo the eaſier to be impoſed upon by the <hi>greater</hi> Craft and Sagacity of our <hi>ghoſtly Adverſaries.</hi> For we muſt yield them the Pre-eminece in <hi>all the powers</hi> of Underſtanding and acting ſuitably to their Diſpoſitions and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. And as our Saviour tells us, that <hi>the Children of this World are in their Generation wiſer than the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 16.8.</note> ſo the Spirits they are <hi>acted</hi> by, have doubtleſs a <hi>ſharper In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight</hi> into the Nature of things than <hi>either</hi> of them, a <hi>ſtronger Judgment</hi> in the fitneſs and choice of Means, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Quickneſs</hi> and <hi>Dexterity</hi> in their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications to them, together with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied Vigour and Diligence, <hi>ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated</hi> by a perfect and incurable Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of God and Goodneſs: Beſides the vaſt Improvements <hi>they</hi> have made by <hi>long</hi> and <hi>ſucceſsfull</hi> Practice in all the <hi>Arts</hi> of Ruin and Seduction.</p>
                  <p>But beſides this <hi>veterane Army</hi> (in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151439:31"/>which not <hi>one</hi> of all the <hi>Tribes</hi> is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſince the <hi>War</hi> began) this <hi>mighty Warriour</hi> has innumerable <hi>other Forces</hi> and <hi>Auxiliaries</hi> to aſſault us with. The ill Men and Examples of the World, which make the far greateſt <hi>Figure</hi> and <hi>Party</hi> in every Age, are all <hi>entire</hi> on his ſide. Yea, all that is called the <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of this World, the <hi>blazing</hi> Honours and Riches of it, its <hi>ſtately</hi> Pomp and Pageantry, attended with all the <hi>Charms</hi> of Wit, Beauty, Parentage, and Power (the <hi>ſplendid Furniture</hi> of Pride and Luxury) do readily contribute <hi>their Service</hi> to him, and <hi>aſſiſt</hi> his Inſtigations to <hi>idolize</hi> and <hi>worſhip</hi> them. Out of theſe <hi>he weaves</hi> his <hi>ſilken</hi> Snares, and forges his <hi>golden</hi> Chains; with <hi>thoſe</hi> to entangle the careleſs and effeminate, and with <hi>theſe</hi> to lead the Worldling <hi>Captive at his Will.</hi> He alſo attempts to <hi>beat us off</hi> from the Paths of Piety and Vertue, with the <hi>Frowns</hi> of this <hi>angry</hi> and <hi>ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> World: and when he finds us <hi>ſtiff</hi> and <hi>reſolute</hi> in our Courſe, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſends whole <hi>Vollies</hi> of Curſes and Reproaches after us, <hi>belcht</hi> from the Mouths of his <hi>impious Children,</hi> on purpoſe to <hi>lame</hi> and obſtruct our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs.</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151439:31"/>Nay, what is <hi>ſadder</hi> than all this, <hi>he</hi> oppoſes our <hi>Salvation</hi> with the <hi>choiceſt</hi> Bleſſings and Aſſiſtances we receive from Heaven,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7.</note> its <hi>immediate</hi> Inſpirations and <hi>divineſt</hi> Gifts; and has a <hi>ſtrange Art</hi> in turning the <hi>beſt Means</hi> and Overtures of <hi>Grace</hi> to his own <hi>malicious</hi> and <hi>deſtructive</hi> Purpoſes; in making <hi>the word of Life a ſavour of Death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.16. 2 Cor. 4.4.</note> and <hi>blinding the Minds of them that believe not, leaſt the Light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God, ſhould ſhine unto them.</hi> And when with all his <hi>Powers of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> he cannot <hi>extinguiſh</hi> this glorious Light, he ſets up <hi>new Lights</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> Revelations againſt it, to <hi>dazle</hi> the minds of <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>unſtable</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, while he <hi>winds</hi> them into his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and through a <hi>Miſt</hi> of obſcure, and a <hi>Maze</hi> of wild and intricate Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, leads them into <hi>damnable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.1.</note> by which (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks) <hi>they bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I might add, that this <hi>ſubtile</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of ours frequently <hi>plays</hi> upon us from our <hi>own Caſtles in the Air;</hi> our <hi>vain</hi> Imaginations and <hi>fooliſh</hi> Fancies, our <hi>high</hi> Conceits of our <hi>own Gifts,</hi> and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151439:32"/>Attainments, our <hi>Ambitious</hi> and <hi>tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> Hopes of earthly <hi>Grandeur</hi> and Felicity, with all the <hi>inchanting</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights and Gayeties of an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice;</hi> our vexatious Fears of <hi>merely contingent</hi> or <hi>improbable</hi> Accidents, our <hi>groundleſs</hi> Confidence and Security in all the <hi>Flatteries</hi> of a ſinfull courſe, and (be that never ſo <hi>long</hi> or <hi>ſinfull</hi>) our <hi>fallacious</hi> reckoning on a <hi>Death-Bed</hi> Repentance after it.</p>
                  <p>The Truth is, the main Strength and Intereſt of <hi>Satan</hi> lies in <hi>our ſelves;</hi> in our weak and ſhallow Judgment of Things, and diſorderly Wills and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections towards them. Our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings are eaſily <hi>miſled</hi> with the <hi>Glare</hi> of ſenſible Objects; and the Luſts <hi>which war in our Members,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jam. 4.1.</note> againſt the Dictates of our Reaſon and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, are a <hi>ſtrong Party</hi> on the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſide, ready on every Inſtigation of <hi>his</hi> to <hi>challenge</hi> their lawleſs Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to betray our Souls into his <hi>mercileſs</hi> hands. And this has been a growing <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to the power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ever ſince the Defection of our firſt Parents; he has gain'd all the ground that we loſt by our fall, and has ſo many <hi>Confederate Luſts</hi> in all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151439:32"/>the <hi>weak</hi> parts of our Nature, that where-ever almoſt he chuſes to aſſault us, he is ſure to find a <hi>well-affected Party</hi> within our ſelves, to promote his banefull and malicious Deſigns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. To this end <hi>he</hi> is very exact in obſerving our <hi>Complexions, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> out of which he ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily <hi>ſpells</hi> our Inclinations, and then applies his Temptations to our particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Likings</hi> and <hi>Averſions;</hi> and ſo fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows <hi>Nature</hi> in the way ſhe is moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to <hi>wander</hi> and <hi>prevaricate</hi> in. This is a ſignal Inſtance of the fatal Craft and Sagacity of our Enemy, to which I will only add two or three remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Advantages the Devil has to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his dark Deſigns, and accompliſh his wicked and deſtructive Projects. The firſt is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſilence of his Attacks, which he uſually begins and carries on with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt <hi>Noiſe</hi> or <hi>Signal of War,</hi> when he is minded to do us the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Miſchief. For tho' his Motions are ſometimes <hi>rapid</hi> and <hi>furious,</hi> as when he raiſes <hi>a Storm</hi> of Perſecution in the Church; yet generally ſpeaking, they are ſo very <hi>ſoft</hi> and <hi>inſenſible,</hi> that without a ſtrict and mighty Care, 'tis
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151439:33"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151439:33"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151439:34"/>hardly poſſible to diſcern them from the Motions of our <hi>own,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 9.55.</note> or (in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) from the <hi>placid</hi> and <hi>gentle</hi> Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Divine Spirit.</hi> So that commonly the <hi>War</hi> is begun before ever we are <hi>aware</hi> of our Enemy; and the Devil is <hi>buſie</hi> with us while he is <hi>fartheſt</hi> from our Thoughts, and we think of nothing leſs than of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Deſigns and Intereſts; nay it may be, while we think <hi>the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> and are <hi>verily perſwaded we are doing God Service.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 26.9. Joh. 16.2.</note> And thus <hi>he</hi> at once conceals his Enmity to us, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters our Infirmities, and pleaſes our Fancies, prevents our Vigilance, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates his <hi>own Party</hi> within us, ſets the Battle in <hi>array,</hi> and many times <hi>ſteals the Victory,</hi> before we have any <hi>Miſtruſt</hi> or <hi>Intimation</hi> of <hi>his tampering</hi> with us, or the leaſt warning from <hi>him</hi> to put our ſelves into a <hi>Poſture of Defence</hi> againſt him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His reſtleſs and indefatigable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in laying his <hi>Snares,</hi> contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>new</hi> Plots and Devices, and improving all Accidents and Advantages to compaſs his pernicious Purpoſes. He is continually <hi>going to and fro in the Earth, and walking up and down in it:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 1.7.</note>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151439:34"/>Traverſing all the ways that <hi>go down to Hell,</hi> or lead up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> and beating out <hi>untrodden</hi> and <hi>nearer</hi> Paths to ruin, than Man himſelf (left to his own <hi>happier</hi> Ignorance) could poſſibly have deviſed to his own Deſtruction. He is never weary of <hi>ill-doing,</hi> he is always moving and coaſting about, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truding into all Places and Companies, liſtening to every Word, and prying into every Corner, to ſpy out oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of <hi>hatching</hi> Miſchief. This is his manner of Life: and in this Poſture St. <hi>Peter</hi> deſcribes him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Your Adverſary the Devil as a roaring Lion, walketh about, ſeeking whom he may devour.</hi> No Place, not <hi>Paradice</hi> it ſelf; no Perſon, not the <hi>purer</hi> Son of God, could eſcape him. The San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary is no <hi>priviledg'd</hi> Place; the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> of our Bleſſed Saviour on Earth,<note place="margin">Mar. 8.33.</note> no certain <hi>Defence</hi> to his domeſtick and beſt-beloved Diſciples; the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Gift of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which caſt the Devil out of his miſerable <hi>Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7. 1 Cor. 10.13.</note> could not ſecure the <hi>Enjoyer</hi> from his Aſſaults and Treacheries. His Temptations are <hi>common to Men,</hi> even the devouteſt Votaries <hi>at the Throne of Grace;</hi> nor does <hi>the ſpecial Preſence</hi> of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151439:35"/>God <hi>in the place where his Honour dwelleth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 1.6.</note> always protect us, from this inſolent Intruder into his <hi>holy Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 12.10.</note> In ſhort he is ſo <hi>impudent</hi> as to accuſe the Children of God <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> and renew his Encounters after the moſt <hi>ſhamefull</hi> Baffles; yea, ſo <hi>maliciouſly</hi> bent upon our Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that he tugs at it <hi>Night</hi> and <hi>Day,</hi> ſullies our Dreams, and defiles our Recreations, perplexes our Buſineſs, and diſtracts our Devotions; a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Snares he lays about our <hi>Tables</hi> and our <hi>Beds;</hi> neither allowing himſelf nor us any <hi>reſt,</hi> till he either <hi>deſpairs</hi> of Succeſs, or <hi>glories</hi> in our ruin.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. His great Artifice in deceiving us with <hi>falſe</hi> Appearances, and raiſing our Expectations of delicious <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> and <hi>Profits</hi> from extremely <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>loſing</hi> Practices. He has a wonderfull <hi>Art</hi> in laying <hi>beautifull</hi> Colours on the moſt deformed and pernicious Actions, and hiding <hi>the Sting</hi> while we taſt <hi>the Sweet</hi> of his <hi>diſguiſed</hi> Dainties. This is indeed his ſovereign and moſt ſucceſsfull <hi>Policy,</hi> to amuſe our Minds with Images of <hi>things which are not,</hi> and entertain our <hi>Fancies</hi> with <hi>gay</hi> and <hi>winning</hi> Objects
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151439:35"/>all the way he is leading us to <hi>ruin.</hi> By this <hi>Decoy</hi> he draws off our Attention from the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reality</hi> of things, and ſo leaves us to <hi>embrace the Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows,</hi> and rue the conſequence of our Folly and Raſhneſs. I will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to determine how far the Devil is <hi>chargeable</hi> with the Crimes which he tempts us to; but this I doubt not may be truly ſaid, That whenever we are ſtrongly tempted to any Action which in <hi>cool thoughts</hi> we know to be <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>hatefull,</hi> and (perhaps) would not do to purchaſe the greateſt <hi>Temporal Good,</hi> the Devil by <hi>myſterious Craft,</hi> and <hi>ſly</hi> Impreſſions on our <hi>Animal Spirits,</hi> raiſes ſuch <hi>fair</hi> and <hi>charming</hi> Ideas of it, as <hi>inſenſibly</hi> alter our opinion of the <hi>dreadfull Act,</hi> gradually ſubdue out <hi>Averſions</hi> to it, and at laſt (if not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by ſeverer Reflections) aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly gain our <hi>Conſent</hi> to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of it.</p>
                  <p>Thus you have ſeen your Ememy at the <hi>head</hi> of his mighty <hi>Armies,</hi> with his wonderfull <hi>Train of Artillery</hi> about him, poſted on the <hi>higher ground,</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to you both in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, tall and terrible</hi> as the <hi>Anakims,</hi> fluſht with <hi>Victory,</hi> and poſſeſſed of
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151439:36"/>many <hi>ſtrong Holds</hi> and <hi>enchanted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles:</hi> full of <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Malice, cloſe</hi> and <hi>ſecret</hi> in his <hi>Motions,</hi> while he puſhes on his Deſigns with a <hi>reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> and <hi>fatal</hi> Diligence, and in a moſt <hi>perfidious</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> manner ſeeks to <hi>play you into ruin,</hi> to make you the <hi>Inſtruments,</hi> and to <hi>pleaſe</hi> you in the <hi>methods</hi> of your <hi>own Deſtruction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After all, our comfort is, that this great and formidable power of the <hi>evil Spirit</hi> is ever under the check of a <hi>ſuperiour</hi> and <hi>infinite</hi> Power, ſo that it cannot exert it ſelf farther than God is pleas'd to <hi>permit</hi> it; the Bounds of whoſe Permiſſions are diſcoverable on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by his Word and Promiſes, of which there may be a fitter occaſion to ſpeak hereafter.</p>
                  <p>And now having view'd the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and detected the <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of this <hi>potent</hi> and terrible Enemy, let us turn the <hi>Perſpective,</hi> and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</p>
                  <p n="2">II. What <hi>Power</hi> we have to <hi>reſiſt the Devil,</hi> and by what means we may effectually ſecure our ſelves againſt him. That the Devil is no <hi>irreſiſtible</hi>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151439:36"/>Enemy, is as clear as that we are both <hi>commanded</hi> and <hi>encouraged</hi> to reſiſt him. For to what purpoſe were it to encounter with <hi>invincible</hi> Power? Or what hope of an Enemy's <hi>flying from us,</hi> that hath <hi>Victory it ſelf</hi> at his Command and Pleaſure? If we muſt <hi>ſink</hi> under his Power, ſerve only to glorifie his <hi>Triumphs,</hi> to furniſh him with <hi>malicious Joy,</hi> and be dragg'd at his <hi>Chariot Wheels,</hi> as the wretched <hi>Captives</hi> of his Wiles and Fallacies, why ſhould we ſtruggle any longer, or think to break the <hi>Adamantine Chains</hi> of our Fate and Miſery? In vain are all good and pious <hi>Endeavours</hi> towards the recovery of our <hi>degenerate</hi> Nature into a ſtate of Virtue and Perfection, if <hi>the Enemy</hi> of all that is good and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous hath an abſolute and uncontroul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Power</hi> to interrupt and ſtifle them. And ſo all the <hi>Motives</hi> of the Goſpel would be <hi>mere Flam</hi> and <hi>Mockery</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Promiſe of an <hi>Aſſiſtance equal</hi> to the Difficulties of our Spiritual Combats; And had God denied us that Aſſiſtance, and for ever abandon'd us to the <hi>Malice</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, there could have been no room <hi>for a Covenant of Grace;</hi> nothing but
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151439:37"/>
                     <hi>a fearfull looking for of Judgment, and fiery Indignation to devour us.</hi> Again, why are we baptized in the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> if there be none to <hi>ſave</hi> us? No eſcape from <hi>the everlaſting Chains pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the Devil and his Angels?</hi> And how is it poſſible to <hi>love</hi> that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>with all my Heart,</hi> and adore him <hi>with all my Soul</hi> (be his Power and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty never ſo immenſe) that ſhould let Hell and Deſtruction <hi>looſe</hi> upon me, when I have no more power to <hi>reſiſt</hi> them, than when I lay in my <hi>Swad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-Bands,</hi> helpleſs and innocent of all actual Crimes? To bring both <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes</hi> of a Contradiction together, or do that which in the <hi>nature</hi> of it can never be done, is more than <hi>Infinite Power</hi> it ſelf can do; and therefore <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom and Goodneſs</hi> cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of frail and finite Creatures, eſpecially under an <hi>Infinite Penalty.</hi> And ſince it is plainly impoſſible to withſtand <hi>irreſiſtible</hi> Power, it can be no leſs than an <hi>Infinite Abſurdity</hi> to ſuppoſe the Enemy of our Salvation to be irreſiſtible.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, there are conſiderable odds between the powers of the <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> Nature, eſpecially
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151439:37"/>ſince we are ſo much <hi>ſhatter'd</hi> by our Fall, and have loſt ſo much of the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour</hi> and <hi>Bravery</hi> of our Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties; but this only proves, that we are no <hi>equal Match</hi> to our Adverſary in <hi>ſingle Combat,</hi> and that we ſtand in need of <hi>better Powers</hi> than our <hi>own</hi> to fight our way through the many <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> and <hi>Difficulties</hi> of our Chriſtian Warfare; and this I eaſily grant. But then it is certain, that the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is, in the Nature of it, <hi>a Confederate War;</hi> that <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelf eſpouſes our Cauſe, and that we ſtill retain thoſe <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>excellent</hi> Faculties, which being <hi>animated</hi> and <hi>ſupported</hi> by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance, and duely <hi>exerciſed</hi> according to the <hi>Chriſtian Diſcipline,</hi> are at leaſt ſufficient to defend us againſt the utmoſt <hi>Efforts</hi> and <hi>Attempts</hi> of Hell. This is the <hi>true ſtate</hi> of the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r</hi> betwixt us and our <hi>inviſible</hi> Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for the clearer Underſtanding of which, I ſhall ſhew theſe three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. That to reſiſt the Devil is only to withſtand his Temptations.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. That we are not deſtitute of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Powers and Aſſiſtances (if we
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151439:38"/>are not wanting to our ſelves) to withſtand the Aſſaults and Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Devil.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. By what means we may effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually reſiſt them.</p>
                  <p n="1">I. For the Firſt, To reſiſt the Devil is only to <hi>withſtand</hi> his <hi>Temptations,</hi> and oppoſe his crafty and malicious Endeavours to betray us into Sin and Miſery. He has indeed <hi>no other way</hi> to aſſault and hurt our Souls, than by <hi>tempting</hi> them to evil; I mean, al long as we are in <hi>a ſtate of Tryal,</hi> and are not <hi>judicially</hi> delivered up to his Rage and Fury. And therefore our <hi>only way</hi> to reſiſt him, is to foil his <hi>Temptations,</hi> and take <hi>effectual</hi> Care that he does not <hi>faſten</hi> any of his Fallacies or Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon us. For 'tis evident, while we are under the <hi>Influence</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> of Divine Grace, that the Devil nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does nor can act <hi>immediately</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Wills,</hi> or force us to do his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure by any <hi>phyſical determining</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whatever he may do with thoſe <hi>miſerable Wretches</hi> whom God hath <hi>forſaken,</hi> and turn'd over to this <hi>dire Executioner</hi> of his Wrath and Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151439:38"/>He has <hi>leave</hi> indeed to bring us to <hi>our Tryal,</hi> and the Deciſion of the <hi>grand Controverſie,</hi> whether we will chuſe to be ſubject to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>him;</hi> but then our <hi>very Tryal</hi> ſuppoſes, that we are not liable to any <hi>compulſive</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining</hi> Power, during the <hi>whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> of it, but are left to our Liberty to <hi>chuſe whom we will ſerve,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Joſh 24.15.</note> and which of the <hi>two</hi> contrary <hi>Maſters</hi> we will <hi>love</hi> and <hi>cleave</hi> unto. For it would be a ſtrange <hi>Tryal</hi> to put men upon Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, that cannot ſtir the leaſt Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to remove them; and when I throw up <hi>a Stone</hi> into the Air, I might as <hi>well</hi> and <hi>wiſely</hi> charge it to lodge it ſelf in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> and not obey <hi>the Laws of Gravity,</hi> or return (as Nature bids it) to the Boſom of its <hi>beloved Center,</hi> as ſuppoſe God hath obliged me to encounter an Enemy, whoſe Power I am <hi>forc't</hi> to obey, who drags and determines my Will which way ſoever he pleaſes, and leads me about <hi>in Triumph,</hi> without the leaſt Ability to <hi>reſiſt</hi> him, or <hi>diſpute</hi> his Pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>But more than this, <hi>the Temptations</hi> of the Devil are as great a <hi>Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> as we can deſire, that he himſelf is conſcious of his <hi>Impotency</hi> to force and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151439:39"/>conſtrain our <hi>Wills,</hi> and that he has no <hi>direct</hi> and <hi>infallible</hi> way to deceive and ruin us. For if he has, why does he uſe ſo much <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Inſinuation</hi> with us, which often fail of the end they are uſed for? Would ſo <hi>malignant</hi> an Adverſary <hi>go about,</hi> as he does, to <hi>charm</hi> us with tempting Objects, and <hi>court</hi> us with a thouſand <hi>Gauds</hi> and <hi>Flatteries</hi> to a wicked Action, while he has Power enough in his hand to <hi>compell</hi> us to it, and knows a much <hi>ſurer</hi> and <hi>ſhorter</hi> way to execute his pernicious Deſigns upon us? If his power was not <hi>inferiour</hi> to his <hi>Malice,</hi> an Enemy ſo utterly deveſted of all Goodneſs, would certainly make us feel the diſmal Effects of it without Mercy or Delay, and not put it to our <hi>Choice,</hi> or leave it to a Tryal of Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, to comply with him or not. Could he <hi>twine</hi> and <hi>bend</hi> our Wills as he pleaſes, and <hi>elicit</hi> what kind of Acts he is moſt delighted and gratified with, he would ſurely never ſuffer us to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe the evil,</hi> or to <hi>chuſe the good.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, 'tis in vain for us to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that can <hi>determine</hi> our Wills: and becauſe it is ſo, and we are expreſsly commanded <hi>to reſiſt the Devil,</hi> we
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151439:39"/>may be ſure he has no ſuch power, and then it can be no part of our Duty to reſiſt it.</p>
                  <p>The meaning therefore of our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance</hi> muſt be, that we reſolutely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Temptations</hi> of the Devil: whether they come <hi>immediately</hi> from himſelf, or from any of his <hi>inſpired</hi> Agents or Inſtruments, whether by way of <hi>external</hi> Repreſentation, <hi>vocal Suggeſtion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 4.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> or <hi>Argument</hi> (with all which he at once accoſted our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) or by ſecret <hi>Strokes</hi> and <hi>internal Impreſſions</hi> upon our Imaginations and Fancies, whereby he aſſiſts the <hi>natural Rhetorick</hi> of outward Objects, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies their <hi>Abſence</hi> by their <hi>Idea's</hi> and <hi>Pictures.</hi> And here he commonly ſhews the <hi>fineneſs</hi> of his Art, by retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Likeneſs,</hi> while he improves the <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Deformities</hi> of Things, according to his Deſign to inflame our <hi>Affections,</hi> or to raiſe our <hi>Averſions</hi> to them. 'Tis beyond our Conception what <hi>variety</hi> of Methods and Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he takes to <hi>beguile</hi> and ſupplant our Souls; and <hi>particularly</hi> what Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage he makes of our <hi>Animal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> for the framing of thoſe little <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pids</hi> and <hi>Images,</hi> which ſeem to play
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151439:40"/>
                     <hi>without Deſign</hi> in our Fancies, but are often <hi>managed</hi> and prepared by him on purpoſe to <hi>entertain</hi> our Minds with <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>idle</hi> Speculations, to ſolicit our <hi>corrupt</hi> Affections, to diſtract our <hi>purer</hi> Thoughts, and obſtruct our moſt ſerious and important Endeavours. But tho' we cannot pry into all the <hi>curious Arts</hi> and <hi>Myſteries</hi> of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Tempter, or tell exactly how he mixes and lays his <hi>Colours</hi> upon the <hi>Tablet</hi> of our Fancies, yet a carefull Obſerver of the <hi>Impreſſions</hi> they make upon his Thoughts and Paſſions, may plainly diſcern the Artiſt by certain <hi>inimitable Strokes</hi> and <hi>Lineaments,</hi> which diſtinguiſh almoſt all his <hi>Pieces,</hi> and which no other <hi>Genius</hi> than himſelf can reach:<note place="margin">2 Sam. 14.19.</note> As <hi>David</hi> diſcovered the <hi>hand of Joab</hi> in the ſly and crafty Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of his <hi>Familiar</hi> of <hi>Tekoah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For inſtance, whenever we find our Inclinations or Paſſions <hi>ruſhing</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Convictions</hi> of our Duty, and claſhing with the beſt <hi>Principles</hi> of our Reaſon and Conſcience: when we feel ſomething <hi>within us</hi> prompting us to break a <hi>Divine</hi> Commandment, in view of the <hi>glittering Vengeance</hi> that hangs directly over the <hi>Tranſgreſſors</hi>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:151439:40"/>of it: when the <hi>Byas</hi> of our Minds, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it was <hi>rightly</hi> ſet, ſuddenly turns the quite <hi>contrary</hi> way: or our Thoughts are <hi>roving</hi> in the midſt of our <hi>Devotions</hi> after <hi>ſecular</hi> and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Objects, or <hi>bewildred</hi> in a <hi>Maze</hi> of <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>diſtracting</hi> Imaginations: When we hate to think, or have the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the cleareſt <hi>Evidence</hi> of Truth, and are angry with the <hi>Light</hi> for detecting our <hi>Follies;</hi> in theſe and many other <hi>Inſtances</hi> we may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly know that we are <hi>tempted of the Devil;</hi> that <hi>now</hi> the evil Spirit is <hi>buſie</hi> with us, <hi>and he that betrayeth us is at hand.</hi> Of this, I ſay, we may be very <hi>certain,</hi> becauſe ſuch <hi>Impulſes</hi> and <hi>Diſorders</hi> in our Spirits do <hi>appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently</hi> promote the Deſigns of <hi>Satan,</hi> and can ſerve <hi>no other</hi> Intereſts than <hi>his;</hi> becauſe they are every way like <hi>him,</hi> and carry his very <hi>Mark</hi> and <hi>Image</hi> in their <hi>Foreheads,</hi> exactly anſwering the <hi>Mein</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> by which the holy Oracles of God have deſcrib'd him to us. And <hi>now</hi> is our time and duty to <hi>reſiſt him,</hi> to break his <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> and defeat his <hi>Temptations</hi> and <hi>Charms:</hi> to ſtand upon the <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of our Nature, and the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151439:41"/>
                     <hi>Honour</hi> of our Chriſtian Profeſſion, and not yield to any of his Inſtigations or Flatteries;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.27.</note> 
                     <hi>i.e. not give place to the Devil</hi> by complying with them, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> interprets St. <hi>James</hi>'s meaning by reſiſting him.</p>
                  <p n="2">II. We are not deſtitute of ſufficient Powers and Aſſiſtances (if we are not wanting to our ſelves) to withſtand the Aſſaults and Temptations of the Devil. For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. We have all the <hi>Natural</hi> Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that are requiſite to reſiſt Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations. We neither want a Power of <hi>diſcerning between good and evil,</hi> or of knowing what we ought to <hi>avoid,</hi> and what to <hi>chuſe</hi> and <hi>practiſe;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can we pretend that we have no power to make a right <hi>Choice</hi> or <hi>Refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal;</hi> for that were to ſay we are no <hi>reaſonable</hi> Creatures, the proper uſe of <hi>Reaſon</hi> being only to direct our <hi>Choice,</hi> and to govern our Actions aright in relation to it. And therefore a <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>good</hi> Creator could never make us <hi>reaſonable,</hi> without making us <hi>free A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents;</hi> and if we were not ſo, there would be no <hi>occaſion</hi> for reſiſting Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, ſince none but a <hi>free Agent</hi> is <hi>capable</hi> of being aſſaulted by them. All
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151439:41"/>Temptations are <hi>levelled</hi> againſt the right uſe of our <hi>Freedom;</hi> and the <hi>only uſe</hi> the Tempter makes of them, is to <hi>betray</hi> our Wills, and <hi>abuſe</hi> our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by them; which ſhews that <hi>he</hi> cannot faſten any <hi>guilt</hi> upon us <hi>againſt our Wills,</hi> and that the <hi>utmoſt</hi> he can do, is to <hi>ſolicit, excite,</hi> and <hi>cheat</hi> us (if we <hi>will</hi> be cheated by <hi>tinſel</hi> and <hi>faithleſs</hi> Promiſes) into a <hi>fatal</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with his Methods of Ruin and Deſtruction. I ſay, if we <hi>will</hi> be cheated, for there is no Neceſſity that we ſhould; our <hi>Freedom</hi> is our own by a <hi>natural</hi> Right, and the exerciſe of it is ſo <hi>eſſential</hi> to our preſent ſtate of <hi>Tryal</hi> and <hi>Probation,</hi> that there is no Fear, if we believe a <hi>Providence</hi> over us, that our Enemy (were it in his Power) ſhould be permitted to <hi>wreſt</hi> it from us. All the Fear is of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> leſt we ſhould <hi>unhappily</hi> uſe our Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and by an <hi>awkard</hi> and <hi>unnatural</hi> Abuſe of it enſlave our <hi>imperial Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> to ſenſual and <hi>Diabolical</hi> Luſts, and ſo for ever make our ſelves miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable by it. We are ſafe in the hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt <hi>Battles</hi> and <hi>Encounters</hi> of our <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual</hi> Adverſaries, ſo long as we are <hi>true</hi> and <hi>faithfull</hi> to the <hi>Rights</hi> and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151439:42"/>
                     <hi>Intereſts</hi> of our <hi>rational</hi> Nature, <hi>i.e.</hi> ſo long as we <hi>judge</hi> nothing but what is <hi>right,</hi> and <hi>chooſe</hi> nothing but what is <hi>virtuous</hi> and <hi>good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither can we complain that we have no power to <hi>correct</hi> the <hi>Levity</hi> of our Thoughts and Fancies, or to order and regulate our <hi>outward Actions.</hi> There is nothing ſo <hi>free</hi> as <hi>Thought,</hi> or more evident than that the Mind of Man has power <hi>within it ſelf</hi> to ſhift the <hi>Scene</hi> of its <hi>Contemplations,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert from one <hi>Imagination</hi> to another, as often as it pleaſes. A man may think of Hell when he is tempted, and of the <hi>all-ſeeing Eye</hi> before he ventures upon <hi>unchaſt Embraces.</hi> And ſo the <hi>Organs</hi> of <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Motion,</hi> the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate <hi>Cauſes</hi> of outward Actions, are very much in our Power: and by guarding theſe <hi>Inlets</hi> of Luſt and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, we certainly avoid the <hi>ſtrongeſt</hi> and moſt <hi>dangerous</hi> Temptations to Sin and Folly, help to ſtarve our <hi>inbred</hi> Coruptions, and cut of all <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with the Enemy, that is ſo much concern'd to <hi>relieve</hi> and <hi>cheriſh</hi> them. And theſe are all the <hi>Natural Faculties</hi> which are requiſite to <hi>defend</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us againſt Temptations.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:151439:42"/>
                  <p n="2">2. We may be ſure of all the <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Aids and Aſſiſtances,</hi> which are neceſſary to enable us to make a vigorous and effectual <hi>Reſiſtance.</hi> For ſince we are ſo much <hi>weakned</hi> by our Fall, and by indulging our <hi>carnal</hi> and corrupt Affections have extremely ſpoil'd the natural <hi>Tone</hi> and <hi>Rectitude</hi> of our Faculties, 'tis apparent that we are never likely of our ſelves (<hi>i.e.</hi> merely by our own Strength and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy) to ſtand the <hi>mighty Shock</hi> of Temptations, which at every <hi>turn</hi> of our Lives and Fortunes are ready to aſſault us: and that the Grace of God is as <hi>neceſſary</hi> to animate and enforce our Endeavours, as our Reſiſtance is to baffle and overcome the Temptations we are aſſaulted with. Now, as in <hi>Reaſon</hi> we may hope, that God will not refuſe to aſſiſt us againſt the <hi>impious</hi> Power and Tyranny of <hi>Satan,</hi> in Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>his undoubted Right</hi> and Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to our Service: ſo to raiſe our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence</hi> in him he has expreſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that <hi>his Grace is ſufficient for us,</hi> yea, to make us <hi>more than Conquerors:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12:9.</note> that <hi>he will give his holy Spirit to them that ask it,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.37. Luk. 11.13. 1 Joh. 3.8.</note> and hath <hi>ſent his own Son from Heaven on purpoſe to deſtroy the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151439:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>Works of the Devil.</hi> To this end <hi>the Captain of our Salvation</hi> ſent forth his <hi>Heraulds</hi> into the World, ſet up his <hi>Standard,</hi> and diſplayed his <hi>Banners</hi> to the Nations, appointing all that <hi>came to him,</hi> or that ſhould <hi>believe in his Name,</hi> to be liſted into <hi>one Army,</hi> or <hi>Church Militant</hi> on Earth, under the <hi>Conduct</hi> of ſuch Generals and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers as ſhould receive <hi>a Commiſſion</hi> from him, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Broad Seal of Heaven</hi> [<hi>As my Father hath ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi> John 20.21.] Then, to animate his <hi>Followers,</hi> he enter'd the Liſts with <hi>the Prince of Darkneſs,</hi> by dying vanquiſht <hi>all-conquering</hi> Death, <hi>and having ſpoiled Principalities and Powers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2.15.</note> 
                     <hi>he made a ſhew of them openly, triumphing over them</hi> by his glorious Reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe are the higheſt Aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we can have, that God hath taken us into his <hi>holy Protection,</hi> and that <hi>he will not ſuffer us to be tempted above our ability:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> 
                     <hi>but will</hi> (according to his Promiſe) <hi>when we are beſet with any Temptation, make a way to eſcape, that we may be able to bear it.</hi> Which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, that his Providence watches over the <hi>Motions</hi> of our Enemies, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151439:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>they are diſpos'd to tempt us <hi>above</hi> our Strength, and that he hath ſet them their <hi>Bounds</hi> which they cannot paſs, viz. that <hi>Meaſure</hi> of Strength which he is alwaies ready to ſupply us with; and then it muſt be our own fault if we don't make a happy End of this <hi>ſharp</hi> and <hi>tedious</hi> War, and follow our glorious Leader into endleſs Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs. 'Tis true, that all the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>victorious</hi> Grace depend upon our earneſt Prayers and Endeavours to acquit our ſelves like <hi>Good Souldiers of Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> But ſurely, if we may have <hi>Grace</hi> for <hi>Asking,</hi> and <hi>Victory</hi> for <hi>Fighting</hi> for it, we cannot deſire either upon <hi>eaſier</hi> Terms: For now all we <hi>Want</hi> falls within the <hi>verge</hi> of our Power, and if we loſe the Victory we know who to thank for it. <hi>The Spirit that is in us is greater</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>than he that is in the World:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4.4.</note> And while we keep him on our ſide we may Juſtly Glory in this <hi>Happy Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> by virtue of which <hi>we can do all things,</hi> that <hi>Omnipotency</hi> it ſelf, guided by Infinite Wiſdom, can do for us. I come now to ſhew,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By what means we may effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſiſt the Aſſaults and Temptations
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151439:44"/>of the Devil. It was an Infinite <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion</hi> in God to offer us an <hi>Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> by the Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iation of his Son, when our Impotency was the <hi>meer</hi> effect of our Folly and Enmity to him. And as in this reſpect we have all imaginable Reaſon to adore the Divine Goodneſs towards us, ſo it is our apparent Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Policy to embrace the <hi>Terms,</hi> and obſerve the <hi>Orders</hi> our great Patron and Ally hath preſcribed to us. And the rather becauſe there is a <hi>Mighty Noiſe</hi> and <hi>Combuſtion</hi> in the World, which <hi>Serves</hi> the Devil under the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence of <hi>Reſiſting</hi> him. There are thoſe that inveigh heartily againſt him (whoſe <hi>Ill Word</hi> he does not much value) and with <hi>Armed</hi> Zeal and Orthodoxy lay about them at a wonderful rate, as if they would drive all <hi>the Powers of Darkneſs</hi> before them,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Herod. Hiſt. lib 1. p. <hi>71, 72.</hi>
                     </note> and carry their Conqueſts to the very <hi>Gates of Deſtruction:</hi> Like that fooliſh People in <hi>Caria,</hi> of whom the Hiſtorian reports, that to drive away their <hi>ſtrange Gods,</hi> they <hi>Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> themſelves, and went up in <hi>Battel array</hi> to the Bordering Mountains, <hi>beat</hi> and <hi>ſtabb'd</hi> the Air with their <hi>Doughty</hi> Weapons, and to <hi>Crown</hi> ſo brave an Act of <hi>Defiance</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151439:44"/>the Baniſhment of thoſe Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Deities.<note place="margin">Eph 6.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſſes</hi> are not to be quell'd with <hi>Martial</hi> Force, or with <hi>Giddy</hi> and <hi>Popular</hi> Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults: They <hi>laugh</hi> (like the <hi>Leviathan</hi> in <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>at the ſhaking of the Spear,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 41.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>9.</note> and are never better <hi>pleaſed</hi> than to ſee Men Tilting with <hi>Luciferian Pride</hi> and <hi>Fierceneſs</hi> at one onothers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ollies and Opinions, quarrelling with every thing they Diſlike in <hi>Others,</hi> and miſtaking the <hi>true ſeat</hi> of War, which certainly is in every man's <hi>Breaſt,</hi> and will find him work enough while there is a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> to tempt him, or but one Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and Unmortified <hi>Luſt</hi> within him. And no leſs Abſurd and Ridiculous is it, to <hi>encounter</hi> the <hi>Devil</hi> with ſenſeleſs and hideous <hi>Forms</hi> of Words, <hi>Spells,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Magical</hi> Rites: Or to Accoſt him with ſuch <hi>Wooden</hi> Artillery as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Exorciſts uſe, and aſcribe a Divine Efficacy to, I mean their <hi>Reliques. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Conſecrated Salt, Holy Water, Breathings</hi> and <hi>Croſſings,</hi> and what they call <hi>the Chriſm of Salvation.</hi> The true Weapons and Methods of our Spiritual Conflicts are extremely different from <hi>theſe,</hi> and all Modern Inventions of <hi>Superſtitious</hi> and <hi>Fanciful</hi> Men: and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151439:45"/>indeed deſerve a much larger Diſcourſe than the remaining Minutes will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, which will therefore oblige me to ſpeak the more briefly of them. The firſt is</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A true and lively Faith in all the great Articles of the Chriſtian Doctrin. Faith is the <hi>Principle</hi> of all Spiritual <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Operations,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Power</hi> of all other Graces is virtually contained in it; the Conſequence of which is, that the Chriſtians Power to reſiſt the Temptations of the Devil is exactly equal to the <hi>Meaſure</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergy</hi> of his Faith.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.12.</note> And hence S. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly calls the Chriſtian Life <hi>the Good Fight of Faith;</hi> and gives the Preeminence to this Grace above all the <hi>Weapons</hi> of our Spiritual Warfare, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Above all take the ſhield of Faith, wherewith ye ſhall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the Wicked.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.4.</note> And <hi>This</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John</hi>) <hi>is the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that overcometh the World, even our Faith.</hi> And a noble Victory it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any the <hi>World it ſelf</hi> ever ſaw, ſince it reaches even <hi>Him</hi> who is call'd <hi>the God of this World:</hi> For the World is the <hi>Great Magazine</hi> of Temptations, out of which the Devil has all along
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151439:45"/>
                     <hi>furniſht</hi> himſelf with the choiceſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terials for his <hi>Wicked</hi> War. Beſides, <hi>to Overcome the World,</hi> is to <hi>Subdue</hi> and <hi>Mortifie</hi> our Inordinate Affections to it; and when they are <hi>Dead,</hi> the Glories and Vanities of this World will affect us no more than the <hi>Flowers</hi> that are ſtrewed upon our <hi>Graves,</hi> or the ſad <hi>Pomp</hi> and <hi>Solemnities</hi> that attend us thither. We ſhall <hi>then</hi> have no Luſts to gratify, being <hi>Dead</hi> to <hi>this</hi> World, and <hi>living</hi> upon the <hi>Faith</hi> and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Better:</hi> and then it will be no longer in the Tempter's Power to <hi>Gull</hi> us with his <hi>Gilded Toys</hi> and <hi>next-to-nothings:</hi> with <hi>his Fairie</hi> Money, and <hi>Phantaſtick</hi> Braveries, with his <hi>Crackling</hi> and <hi>Blazing</hi> Honours, or the <hi>Guilty</hi> and <hi>Griping</hi> Pleaſures with which he <hi>liberally</hi> Rewards his <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.1.</note> 
                     <hi>The Evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> which is the Life and Eſſence of our <hi>Faith,</hi> will give us ſuch a Proſpect of <hi>Celeſtial</hi> Glory and Happineſs, as will raiſe our Spirits to the Nobleſt <hi>Heights,</hi> and darken all the <hi>Splendor</hi> and <hi>Gayety</hi> of this Tempting Life: It will alſo inſpire us with Invincible For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in the ſharpeſt <hi>Fight of Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.32. Heb. 12.2.</note> while we <hi>look unto Jeſus the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151439:46"/>and Finiſher of our Faith,</hi> and learn of him, <hi>for the Joy that is ſet before us, to endure the Croſſes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the Shame</hi> and Reproaches of this Angry and Virulent World. So that by <hi>Overcoming the World,</hi> i.e. <hi>Mortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> our Affections to it by a lively Faith in God and our Redeemer, we ſpoil the Tempter's Deſigns, drive the <hi>Enemy</hi> out of his <hi>Head Quarters,</hi> nail up his <hi>Murdering Cannon,</hi> and render all his <hi>Great Engines</hi> of War utterly uſeleſs and unſerviceable againſt us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Frequent Application to God by Devout and Fervent Prayers to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us from the <hi>Danger,</hi> and aſſiſt us in the <hi>hour</hi> of Temptation. To this Relief we are directed by our Saviour, who taught his Diſciples to Pray, that they might <hi>not be led,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 11.4.22.40.</note> and that they might <hi>not enter into Temptation:</hi> The meaning of which could not be, that we ſhould beg the Favour of God to be <hi>wholly</hi> exempted from all <hi>Spiritual Trials,</hi> or deſire a clear and abſolute Diſcharge from the <hi>Chriſtian War:</hi> For that were to Pray againſt ſome of the <hi>beſt Means</hi> for Implanting, Exerciſing and Improving Grace, and againſt all Occaſions of <hi>Victory</hi> and <hi>Triumph,</hi> and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151439:46"/>to preſcribe a <hi>new Method</hi> and <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> to God for the Training us up to Eternal Life and Glory, contrary to that which his other Children have been <hi>alwaies</hi> accuſtom'd to. Our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's meaning therefore muſt be, that whereas in our preſent Circumſtances we are <hi>ſurrounded</hi> with innumerable and ſore Temptations, we ſhould pray to our Heavenly Father to <hi>Relieve</hi> us, and not ſuffer us to be <hi>Over power d</hi> or to enter too far into the <hi>Danger</hi> of being worſted by them. And this is ſo much our <hi>Intereſt,</hi> that were there no ſhadow of <hi>Duty</hi> or <hi>Piety</hi> in it, one would think a Senſible Man ſhould not need any other Incentive to it. For is it not an <hi>Ineſtimable</hi> Privilege, that my <hi>Safety</hi> lies in one that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands all the <hi>Powers</hi> of Nature, and the Angels of <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> and has promiſed that nothing ſhall <hi>tempt me above my Power?</hi> As it is impoſſible any thing ſhould, if I will make <hi>his</hi> Power <hi>mine,</hi> which by humble and fervent Prayer I am ſure to do; and ſince my Prayer can reach him every moment, ſhall I wave <hi>his</hi> Defence, vainly rely on my <hi>own</hi> Strenth (at which my Enemy laughs) and venture
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151439:47"/>
                     <hi>alone</hi> into the Battel amidſt all the mighty <hi>Darts</hi> and <hi>Fire</hi> of Hell, and thereby loſe an <hi>Immortal</hi> Soul, and with it a <hi>Victory</hi> ſo eaſie to be gain'd, over which there hangs an <hi>Eternal Crown?</hi> Such Preſumption as this is the higheſt Provocation to Almighty God to forſake us in our greateſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, while we carry it as if we would <hi>Steal</hi> a Victory without him, or tamely give place to the Devil, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than be obliged to <hi>Him</hi> for it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Good Principles of Life and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice are an admirable Fence and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt Temptations. Theſe, like the <hi>Ballaſt</hi> in the Ship, will keep the Soul <hi>Tight</hi> and <hi>Steddy</hi> while the Man is <hi>Floating</hi> on the Waves, driven by the Angry Winds, and toſs'd by the Changes and Accidents of the <hi>Fickle</hi> and <hi>Tempeſtuous</hi> World. Thus, we ſee, in all the <hi>Whirlings</hi> and <hi>Revolutions</hi> of State, as well as thoſe of a private For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, 'tis the Man of Principles ſtill, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls him) the ſolid <hi>ſquare</hi> Man, who has a <hi>baſis</hi> of Integrity on every ſide, that bravely Out-rides the <hi>Storm,</hi> and <hi>ſmiles</hi> at the Dangers which loudly <hi>Threaten</hi> him. And for thoſe <hi>becalming</hi> Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151439:47"/>which lie in <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality,</hi> a Man that has ſettled his courſe of Life the contrary way, that ſteers by <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Vertuous</hi> Principles, is in very little danger of coming with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reach of their Allurements and charms. Having found the <hi>Pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of Religion, and <hi>taſted the Delights of the World to come,</hi> he is prepared againſt the Temptations of <hi>this:</hi> He knows better things than to act againſt his Beſt <hi>Judgment, Experience</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt,</hi> than to forego his Innocence, to <hi>Ruffle</hi> his peacefull Mind, and forfeit the Love and Favour of God, only to enjoy the ſhort Pleaſures of <hi>Senſe,</hi> which the <hi>Meaneſt Soul</hi> in the World could never find any competent Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in. And hence it is <hi>Remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> that Good Men are no leſs the <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> of the World, when through Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize or Inadvertency they <hi>fall into the Snare of the Devil,</hi> than when they <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly withſtand</hi> the greateſt Temptations, and <hi>maintain</hi> their Integrity without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>viſible</hi> ſupport beſides it.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A Right Underſtanding of the <hi>Wiles</hi> and <hi>Stratagems</hi> of <hi>Satan.</hi> 'Tis no unuſual thing with him, ſince <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Immortality</hi> are brought <hi>to Light</hi>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:151439:48"/>by the Goſpel,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.11.</note> to <hi>transform himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of Li ht,</hi> and play the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> under <hi>the Prophet's Mantle;</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude poor <hi>Ignorant</hi> Souls with <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit</hi> Miracles and Prophecies, <hi>Corrupt</hi> Gloſſes and Interpretations of <hi>Scripture,</hi> and wondrous <hi>ſhews</hi> of <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Self-denial,</hi> beyond the line of Mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the utmoſt ſtretch and poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Humane Frailty. Too often he <hi>betrays</hi> Men of Rare and Lively <hi>Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> into <hi>Novel</hi> and <hi>Fond</hi> Conceits, to the apparent and mighty Prejudice of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Piety,</hi> and the enſnaring of ſome of the moſt <hi>Paſſionate</hi> Lovers of the <hi>Beauties of Holineſs.</hi> By varniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Old</hi> exploded <hi>Errours</hi> with <hi>New Phraſes</hi> and <hi>Fallacies,</hi> he recommends them for <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Choice</hi> Diſcoveries of <hi>Goſpel Truths:</hi> And when he is moſt intent on diſturbing the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Harmony</hi> of the Church, he common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adds ſome <hi>Immunities</hi> and <hi>Favours</hi> of his <hi>Own</hi> to the <hi>Royal Charter</hi> of Chriſtian Liberty; for the Currency of which <hi>he</hi> Inſpires his <hi>Miniſters</hi> with Invincible Aſſurance, and with Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Arts of Inſinuation and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:151439:48"/>
                  <p>With theſe and other ſpecious <hi>Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> does the Devil play upon the <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of many that warmly profeſs the Goſpel, and under colour of <hi>Reſiſting</hi> him and his <hi>Doctrines</hi> engage them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Power of Godlineſs.</hi> It concerns us therefore to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his <hi>Methods,</hi> and to <hi>Match</hi> his Policies, by furniſhing our ſelves with <hi>the Wiſdom which is from above,</hi> of which the Holy Scriptures are a moſt Rich and Invaluable <hi>Treaſury.</hi> By the Light of this <hi>Sacred Lamp</hi> we may both diſcover the Tremendous <hi>Depths of Satan,</hi> and the certain way to <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine</hi> and <hi>Defeat</hi> them. Here we have a ſafe and ample <hi>Proſpect</hi> of all the chief Battels that were fought for ſeveral thouſand years, between the Greateſt <hi>Worthies</hi> and <hi>Champions</hi> of former Ages, and this <hi>All-defying</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of theirs, together with the Good and III <hi>Conduct,</hi> and the various <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes</hi> and <hi>Occurrences</hi> on either ſide. Here we read of the famous Tryal of Skill <hi>in the Land of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 1.11, 12. Numb. 26.65.</note> of the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Slaughter of <hi>a Falſe-hearted</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> without a <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Enemy; of many <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roic</hi> Actions of <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151439:49"/>and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and other <hi>Excellent</hi> Men, not without ſome deplorable Mixtures of <hi>ſinfull Failings,</hi> purpoſely written for our <hi>Admonition.</hi> Interwoven with theſe Relations we every where meet with the <hi>Wiles</hi> and <hi>Stratagems,</hi> the <hi>Windings</hi> and <hi>Fallacies</hi> of the <hi>old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:</hi> the diligent Obſervation of which, added to the skill we have <hi>purchas'd</hi> by <hi>dear</hi> Experience, or at <hi>eaſie Rates</hi> may be gain'd by the Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and Miſadventures of <hi>others,</hi> will be ſo much <hi>Spiritual Armour,</hi> and ward off many <hi>deadly</hi> and <hi>ſurprizing</hi> Strokes from our <hi>ever-waking</hi> and <hi>intriguing</hi> Enemy. For what is eaſier, when we ſee the <hi>Train,</hi> than to avoid <hi>the Blow? In vain</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is the Net ſpread in the ſight of any Bird.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 1.17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Vigilance and Sobriety are alſo neceſſary to defeat the Policies and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions of Satan. If we have not a <hi>Preſence of Mind</hi> to diſcern an <hi>approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Danger, if we <hi>ſleep over</hi> our oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of <hi>reſiſting,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26.12, 15.</note> like King <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>careleſs</hi> General, in uſeleſs Armour while their <hi>Bolſters</hi> were deckt and guarded with <hi>glittering Weapons,</hi> 'tis no wonder if our <hi>watchfull Adverſary</hi> invade us when we leaſt expect him;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151439:49"/>
                     <hi>deride</hi> our Sloth and Folly, and <hi>ſteal</hi> away the <hi>Arms</hi> that ſhould defend us from him. The Devil is as <hi>ſubtle</hi> and <hi>circumſpect</hi> as he is malicious, and doubtleſs gets a great deal more by <hi>ſurprizing</hi> us, than by all his <hi>fair</hi> Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles and <hi>formal</hi> Encounters with us. He cares not much to aſſault us when he ſees we are <hi>prepared</hi> for him: and were it not to <hi>keep his hand in,</hi> or that he hopes to tire us out with <hi>watching</hi> and <hi>obſerving</hi> his Motions, with ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſo often</hi> to Heaven, and waiting <hi>ſo long</hi> (as becomes us) for Relief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he would ſurely never trouble us with ſo many <hi>frivolous</hi> and <hi>forlorn</hi> Temptations, as he frequently does. It concerns us therefore (as we are often warn'd) to be very cautious of our <hi>wakefull</hi> Enemy, <hi>to watch leſt we enter into Temptation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 26.41. 1 Pet. 5.8. Luck 21.34.</note> and to be <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> that we may be <hi>vigilant;</hi> to <hi>take heed leſt our Hearts be over-charg'd with ſurfeiting, and drunkenneſs, and the cares of this life, and ſo the evil day,</hi> and the evil Spirit, <hi>come upon us unawares.</hi> For, alas! what <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> are we like to make, while we <hi>ſtagger</hi> with Wine? While our our <hi>Spirits</hi> are <hi>diſſolved</hi> in Luxury and Pleaſure, our
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151439:50"/>
                     <hi>Hands bound</hi> with Multiplicity of Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, and our <hi>Hearts diſquieted</hi> and <hi>broken</hi> with the vexatious Purſuits and Diſtractions of this <hi>preſent evil World?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Laſtly, Induſtry and Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in our Callings are great Securities againſt the Baits and Temptations of the Devil. The wiſe and good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God hath <hi>ſo happily</hi> ordered our Affairs in this World, that there is really more ſatisfaction and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantneſs in an <hi>active</hi> and <hi>virtuous</hi> courſe than was ever found in all the <hi>envied State</hi> of the moſt <hi>ſplendidly</hi> idle and unprofitable Life. And methinks this <hi>Argument</hi> alone ſhould be enough to convince an obſerving <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> that Infinite Wiſdom ſits at the <hi>Stern</hi> of the World; ſince he cannot but perceive that the <hi>leaſt honourable</hi> and <hi>moſt toil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi> Employments (which are moſt <hi>neceſſary</hi> to the welfare of Mankind) are delicious <hi>Sport</hi> and <hi>Recreation</hi> to the patient Labourer, in compariſon of the <hi>Fatigue of having nothing to do,</hi> and the <hi>tireſome</hi> Vanity of <hi>waſting</hi> time for want of skil or buſineſs to employ it. And hence it is, that Men that are <hi>diligent</hi> and <hi>faithfull</hi> in their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings do generally meet with <hi>fewer
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151439:50"/>Temptations,</hi> and find <hi>more</hi> Strength and Spirit to <hi>reſiſt</hi> them, than thoſe that are <hi>foften'd</hi> with <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> and have ſo much <hi>time</hi> upon their hands that they are willing to afford it at the <hi>cheapeſt rate,</hi> and take even <hi>the Wages of Sin,</hi> rather than <hi>work out their own Salvation.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> A Man that lives upon his <hi>honeſt</hi> Labour and Induſtry has ſomething elſe to do than to <hi>ſport</hi> and <hi>drink</hi> away his time, or to <hi>fool</hi> it away in <hi>dreſſing, gaming,</hi> and other <hi>lurching</hi> and prodigal Expences; and therefore when the Devil comes to tempt him to theſe and the like <hi>ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and extravagant Courſes, he eaſily <hi>detects</hi> his Fallacies and <hi>reſiſts</hi> his Charms. He finds his <hi>Diligence</hi> brings him <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Honours,</hi> and that his <hi>faithfull</hi> Dealing keeps his Mind al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <hi>ſerene</hi> and <hi>chearfull;</hi> he <hi>feels</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſatisfied in his virtuous and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious way, and knows that Vice and the Devil are <hi>Cheats,</hi> but that God and Goodneſs will plentifully <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all them that diligently ſeek them.</hi> It remains, in the third and laſt place, to ſhew</p>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151439:51"/>
                  <p n="3">III. What Aſſurance we have that the Devil will yield to our Reſiſtance, and <hi>flee from us.</hi> By his <hi>flying</hi> is ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meant his <hi>withdrawing</hi> his great <hi>Temptations,</hi> and leaving us to <hi>enjoy the Victories</hi> we have <hi>fairly</hi> won by our vigorous and undaunted <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> of him. Every <hi>Repulſe</hi> we give him drives him to a greater <hi>diſtance</hi> from us, and makes him more <hi>wary</hi> for the future how he repeats his <hi>Errour,</hi> and <hi>meddles</hi> any more with thoſe that are clad in <hi>Armour of Light,</hi> and to his peril he has found too ſtrong and well-appointed for him. So that if every way we <hi>guard</hi> our ſelves againſt him, if we <hi>mortifie</hi> our Boſom-Luſts, clear our Hearts of the <hi>Love</hi> of this World, and <hi>fortifie</hi> every weak Grace and good Inclination in us, we ſhall ſoon be <hi>eaſed</hi> of our Adverſary, and by degrees <hi>advance</hi> to that <hi>ſecure</hi> and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable</hi> State St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks of, as the <hi>peculiar</hi> Privilege and Happineſs of eminent and victorious Chriſtians (whom he deſcribes by their <hi>high</hi> and <hi>divine</hi> Extraction) 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is begotten of God keepeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that wicked one toucheth him not.</hi> And, <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:51"/>
                  <p>A DISCOURSE Shewing the <hi>CONSISTENCY</hi> OF God's Infinite Goodneſs With His FOREKNOWLEDGE Of the <hi>FALL of MAN.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL WHALEY,</hi> A.M. Rector of <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Brab. Aylmer</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1698.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:52"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:52"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>THE Minutes of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe were formerly ſent to a Perſon of good Quality, who was pleaſed to deſire my Thoughts upon the Queſtion, <hi>How the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Goodneſs of God was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with his Foreknowledge of the Fall of Man?</hi> I was well aſſured this Deſire did not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from an ill Tincture of Mind, from a Sceptical Levity, or any other Principle but what became a very ſerious and prudent Inquirer; accordingly I applied my ſelf to one of that Character; and am
<pb facs="tcp:151439:53"/>now encouraged by the Succeſs of that Eſſay, to publiſh this little Tract; which, I heartily wiſh, may be uſefull alſo to another ſort of Inquirers, I mean thoſe who in their own Defence are forc't to <hi>queſtion</hi> every thing in Religion, be it never ſo clear, if it does not ſhine upon their ill-choſen and fallacious Intereſts.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>N. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="discourse">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:151439:53"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Q.</hi> How is the Infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God conſiſtent with his Foreknowledge of the Fall of Man?</head>
                  <p>THere are two things evidently Implied in this Caſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Infinite Goodneſs of God: which duely conſidered will effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcatter all our Melancholy Thoughts, and Miſgiving Apprehenſions of his Arbitrary Dealings with us. For if God is Infinitely Good in himſelf, he muſt be <hi>naturally</hi> diſpoſed to be Kind and Beneficent to his Creatures: and therefore he could not make them with a Deſign to make them Miſerable, either in reſpect of their Original Frame, or for want of due Conduct to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Good and Happy ends for which by his Sovereign Pleaſure they were at firſt Created.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His Fore-knowledge of the Thoughts and Free Actions of Men,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151439:54"/>which is the Higheſt and moſt Perfect Degree of Knowlege. It is a far leſs Perfection to Know what is Paſt, or Preſent, or Dependent upon Neceſſary Cauſes, than merely by the <hi>Force</hi> of Thought to Foreſee the Motions of Voluntary Agents, and Infallibly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover which way they will Determine themſelves. This is the wonderfull Prerogative of the Divine Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which being Infinite (as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſtyles it) muſt be extended to all the Objects of Knowledge,<note place="margin">Pſ. 147.5.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the Free and Future Actions of Men: For, that they are within the ſphere of Omniſcience, the Actual Completion of many Eminent Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in Scripture is a plain Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch as the Eagle-eyed Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an could never bear the Dazling Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of, but Flutters and is forc'd to ſhew his Dizzineſs and Blindneſs, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as it is Objected to him. And ſurely nothing can derogate more from the Wiſdom of our Creator, than to ſay of him, that he knew not what he was doing when he made Man (the Maſter-piece of the viſible Creation:) Or that he did not ſee the End of his Work, when he Inſpired him with
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151439:54"/>Reaſon and Freedom; as certainly he did not, if he did not foreſee his Fall, and Diſcover what Uſe he would make of his Faculties, till his Creature diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to him.</p>
                  <p>But it is not my preſent Buſineſs to clear the Doctrine of Preſcience, but ſuppoſing God's Foreknowledge of the Fall of Man, to ſhew the Conſiſtency of it with his Infinite Goodneſs, which I ſhall endeavour to do by the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Following Propoſitions.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> 1. That the moſt Perfect and Comprehenſive Thought or Notion we can have of God, is that he is a Being Infinite in all Kinds of Perfection, ſuch as Exiſtence, Power, Knowledge, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Holineſs, Juſtice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> each of which, to the utmoſt Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of Perfection, is no leſs Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to the Divine Nature, than the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Reaſoning is to the Humane: So that whenever we ſpeak of God, we are ſuppoſed to ſpeak of that Glorious Being that has all Tranſcendent Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies in himſelf. And hence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Attributes or Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God are very agreeable and conſiſtent one with another: or that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151439:55"/>there is a mutual <hi>Concent</hi> and <hi>Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> between them, without the leaſt Jar or Contrariety to obſtruct their happy Union in the ſame individual and ever bleſſed Nature.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Since all Perfections are united in the divine Nature, and eſſential to it, they muſt be alſo inſeparable one from another: ſo that God muſt be infinitely good and juſt at the ſame time that he is infinitely wiſe, power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and holy, <hi>i.e.</hi> all his Perfections muſt be co-exiſtent, ſeeing they all Center in one and the ſame unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Nature. And hence we may be ſure that God never <hi>deveſts</hi> himſelf of one Attribute, when ever he chuſes to glorifie another, how inconſiſtent ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they may ſeem to our weak and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adequate Apprehenſions of them. And therefore</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We muſt expect no act of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from God, but what is conſiſtent with infinite Knowledge, Wiſdom, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Holineſs: nor need we fear any Severity or Puniſhment from him, but what a good, a holy and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God can inflict upon us.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Hence it follows, that no <hi>ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Contrariety between the Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151439:55"/>of God, or any of his Actions and Dealings with his Creatures, is any <hi>real</hi> Argument againſt the Conſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of them. For inſtance, it may ſeem to ſome very ſerious Perſons to reflect upon the Goodneſs of God, at the ſame time to foreſee the Sin of Man, and to put him into a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in which he might ſin and be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, which (they will ſay) might have been prevented by ſtaying his creating hand. But how hard ſoever it may be for a finite Underſtanding to account for it; this no reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Objection againſt the Goodneſs of our Maker; it being no leſs certain that God is good, than that Man is created and fallen, or that there is ſuch a glorious Being as God in the World; for, if ſuch an one there is, he is infinitely perfect, and then he muſt be infinitely good, and was ſo when he made the World, and will be ſo to eternal Ages, being <hi>the ſame</hi> yeſterday, to day, and for ever. This is as bright a Truth as any is within the whole Circle of Science. There is no foundation of Certainty, if there is no God; and there can be none that is not perfectly good.</p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:151439:56"/>
                  <p>Let us therefore hold to this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, that God is Infinite in Goodneſs, and Knowledge, and all other Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and the conſequence will be, that his creating Man after he had foreſeen his Fall, is no reaſonable Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt his Goodneſs, or any of his glorious Attributes; becauſe it is impoſſible for a Being that has all poſſible Perfection in himſelf, to act beneath the Dignity of his Nature, or to injure his Creatures by doing any thing which they might juſtly to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity accuſe him of.</p>
                  <p>This, I confeſs, does not eaſe us of the difficulty of apprehending, how it conſiſts with the Goodneſs of God to make a Creature, who (he knew) would ſin and be miſeralbe: But then the greater that Difficulty is, the more clearly it ſhews the Weakneſs and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competency of our Underſtandings to cenſure and ſit in Judgment upon the Actions of God; and that it becomes us to content our ſelves with what we certainly do or may know and believe concerning him and his Attributes. <hi>Who art thou,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 9.20, 21.</note> O man, that replieſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God? Shall the thing formed ſay to him that formed it, Why haſt thou
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151439:56"/>made me thus? Hath not the Potter power over the Clay?<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> 
                     <hi>Oh the depth of the Riches both of the Wiſdom and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God! How unſearchable are his Judgments, and his Ways paſt finding out!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> II. Tho' God is infinitely good in himſelf, we muſt not expect that he ſhould make his Creatures perfectly good and happy. For, as abſolute Perfection is eſſential to the Notion of God, ſo is Dependence and Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Notion of a Creature: which proves that there are Degrees of Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which are not communicable to Creatures; and for thoſe which are, all we can expect from a good Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is, that he ſhould communicate ſuch competent Degrees of Goodneſs to every Creature, as are agreeable to their ſeveral Natures and Capacities, and conducive to wiſe and excellent ends, <hi>i.e.</hi> that every thing ſhould be made good in its Kind, and in Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the good end of its Creation. And this Rule (as <hi>Moſes</hi> tells us) was exactly obſerved to the leaſt Mite or Inſect. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. <hi>And God ſaw every thing that he had made, and behold it
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151439:57"/>was very good:</hi> Which could not have been ſaid of every Creature, if there was any Defect in the Creation of Men or Angels, who are the Top and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Creation. And if they were <hi>made very good</hi> in the unerring Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, tho we may fancy ſtill that they might have been made <hi>better,</hi> we cannot accuſe the Goodneſs of God for making them as they were made, both becauſe he judges infinitely better than we do, and becauſe to be <hi>made ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good</hi> implies no leſs, than that God advanc't them at firſt to a very happy Condition, and gave them all that was needfull to ſecure and improve their Happineſs; and more than this we have Reaſon to think was not ſuitable to his infinite Wiſdom; and ſince God is as wiſe as he is good, all we can promiſe our ſelves is, that he will do all the good that can be wiſely done, but no more.</p>
                  <p>The Summ of this is, that abſolute and perfect Goodneſs being eſſential to God, we muſt not look for it in the Creatures, whoſe Natures are uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of it: and that relative or creating Goodneſs, is and muſt be commenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to the Nature of Creatures, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151439:57"/>the good ends for which they were created. And then, if God gave Man an excellent Nature, and endued him with all the Perfections of Mind and Body that were requiſite to his tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and eternal Happineſs, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that he has done all that became a good and bountifull Creator to do for him.</p>
                  <p>Now let us put the matter upon this Iſſue: all that was requiſite to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or future Happineſs of Man was provided to his hand, when God made him a reaſonable, innocent and immortal Being, and gave him power to ſecure and enlarge his Happineſs by acting according to the Dictates of his Reaſon, and perſevering in his Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Obedience to his Maker. Was not this an Act of adoreable Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? And did it not deſerve the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Returns of <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Gratitude</hi> to the Author of it? But where was then the Error in Man's Creation? Was it that it brought him into a State of Subjection to his Maker? But this is eſſential to every Creature; and by this Argument there ought to have been no Creation at all. Or was it, that Man being made a free and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151439:58"/>Being, might poſſibly abuſe the Goodneſs of his Maker, tranſgreſs his Commandments, and ſo make himſelf miſerable, when nothing but himſelf could do it. 'Tis true, this was the primitive State both of Angels and Men: but the queſtion is, where is the fault of it, when both the one and the other were made faultleſs and happy, and might have continued ſo (had they pleaſed) for ever? If there was no fault in the Creature, there could be none in the Creator: and then it will be hard to find one any where elſe.</p>
                  <p>But ſtill ſome Men cannot bring their Minds to apprehend, but that it muſt needs argue a Defect in creating Goodneſs, to make a Creature of the moſt curious Form, and the nobleſt Endowments of Mind and Spirit, that can act below the Dignity of its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Nature, and by ſinning make it ſelf miſerable. But I would fain know what rational Ground theſe Men have for ſo tranſcendent a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit as this. Would they be more than Angels, or any Creature they can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly frame an Idea of? And becauſe God is unchangeably good and happy, will they charge his Goodneſs for not
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151439:58"/>making them equal to him? They don't uſe to queſtion the Goodneſs of God for making ſo vaſt a difference as he has done between the ſeveral Orders of Creatures, for not giving every Plant the Fragrancy of a Roſe, or every Flower the Beauty of a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip, or every Beaſt the Courage and Majeſty of a Lion; or for making the Earth and all the Furniture of this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour World <hi>for the Service of Men.</hi> And far leſs Reaſon they have to tax him for creating Man for his own <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable</hi> and peculiar <hi>Service,</hi> which is the higheſt Freedom and Glory of a Creature; or for not ſetting him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Angels of Heaven, as he muſt have done, if he had created him in a fixt and unchangeable State of Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And why ſhould they imagine that God cannot, without reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Goodneſs, make a reaſonable Creature ſubject to Change and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to Sin and Miſery, when they ſee a World of ſuch Creatures before them? Do they really think that God created the World only to diſparage his Goodneſs, and expoſe the beſt of his Creatures to Miſery? Does every free and reaſonable Being reproach the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151439:59"/>creating Goodneſs of God? If it does not, there could be no Fault in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, though it might ſin and be miſerable; if it does, then in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Equity God ought not to have made one reaſonable Creature or free Agent: and then he could not have made one happy Creature, ſince none but reaſonable Creatures are capable of true and proper Happineſs. And what is the conſequence of all this, but that God ought to have made no World at all? For if Honour and Equity would not ſuffer him to furniſh a World with reaſonable Creatures, who might abuſe their Reaſon and be miſerable: Honour, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs would not ſuffer him to make a World without them, ſince ſuch a World would not be worthy of its Creator, having no Creature in it that could relliſh his Goodneſs, celebrate his Praiſe, partake of any of his Moral Perfections, or receive any true Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs from him; and better none, than ſuch a dull, uſeleſs, and inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant World as this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> III. That nothing could bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter become the Goodneſs and all other
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151439:59"/>Perfections of God, than to make a Creature after his <hi>own Image,</hi> becauſe this is the higheſt Manifeſtation of creating Goodneſs. The Image of God is the moſt abſolute Pattern of Being and Excellency; and therefore to make a Creature after his Image, is to make the moſt abſolute and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Creature: and to do this is moſt agreeable to the Divine Perfections; and then nothing can be more unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable than to ſuppoſe any Diſcord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them in the Accompliſhment of it. When God therefore ſaid, <hi>Let us make Man in our Image,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> after our Likeneſs,</hi> 'tis plain that this was done with the Approbation of all his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes; and that there was nothing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his making Man a reaſonable and free Agent, and endowing him with divine and virtuous Principles, becauſe this was to make him after the Image of his Maker. Now a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Creature having Freedom of Choice, may chuſe well or ill; for though he cannot chuſe Evil for its own ſake, becauſe there is nothing in the Nature of Evil to recommend it to him: yet when it is varniſht with a ſhew of Pleaſure or Advantage, that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151439:60"/>is, when it puts on a Vizzor or Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of good (which all evil may do, except apparent and immediate Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) it may be unhappily miſtaken, and ſo choſen for it. 'Tis certain there was no natural Propenſity to evil in the original Conſtitution of Men or Angels: but ſtill where there is a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of choice, there is and muſt be a Poſſibility of chuſing Wrong; for he only is free that chuſes the good or evil which he had power not to have choſen: if he could not refuſe either, he cannot be ſaid to act upon Choice, but Neceſſity. And indeed the very Notion of <hi>Moral Evil</hi> implies a chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or voluntary Agent, there being no other way for ſin to enter into the World, but by being <hi>choſen,</hi> i.e. by the Act of ſome voluntary Agent which might chuſe amiſs; and ſo a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Agent implies a Poſſibility of ſinning. Man therefore might ſin, tho' he was made <hi>very good,</hi> or, as it became his Creator to make him, a free and reaſonable Being, <hi>after his own Image and Likeneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But here the Queſtion may be asked; Might not God have given Man a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Soul without a Liberty of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151439:60"/>Choice? and ſo prevented the Entrance of Sin into the World? I anſwer, 'tis hard to ſay what God cannot do mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with reſpect to his infinite Power, ſince by that he can do all things that do not imply a Contradiction in the Nature of them. But then it is utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unaccountable, that a wiſe, a good, and a juſt God ſhould make a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only to underſtand what is fit and right to be done, and not give him a power to chuſe what is good and right. For what uſe is there of Reaſon, but to teach us what we ſhould chuſe? And what advantage is it to know this, if we can make no uſe of our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as certainly we cannot, if we have no <hi>Faculty</hi> to chuſe what we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to be good and excellent? What were we the better for knowing there is a God and a Heaven, if we could not love and chuſe them for our Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? 'Tis not the Knowledge of any Excellency that can make us happy, without a Diſpoſition to enjoy it; and what we are diſpoſed to enjoy we love, deſire, and chuſe to have a Propriety in; and then a Creature that cannot chuſe at all, cannot be happy: and then, I am ſure, he cannot be made after the Image of God.</p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:151439:61"/>
                  <p>Are not Moral Goodneſs and Virtue abſolutely neceſſary to make a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creature happy? And does not Morality in the Nature of it imply a <hi>free</hi> as well as a <hi>reaſonable</hi> Agent? Do not the greateſt Pleaſures in the World, in the Judgment of the wiſeſt and beſt Men, flow from this Reflection, that they have <hi>choſen the better part,</hi> and preferred the pleaſing of God, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of their Nature, and the Peace of their Conſciences, before the Charms and Gratifications of Senſe, when they might have choſen and enjoyed them? Now, if the great uſe of Reaſon be to guide our Choice, and if Liberty of Choice be neceſſary to the Happineſs of a reaſonable Being, it is a plain Contradiction to the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, (how fecible ſoever it may be to his Power) to ſuppoſe him to make a reaſonable Creature without a Liberty of Choice.</p>
                  <p>Again, A Being that has no Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to diſpoſe of its own Actions, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deſerve well or ill, or be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God for any thing it does, or does not do. and then were the World made up of ſuch Creatures, there could be no ſuch thing as Religion in it, no
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151439:61"/>room for Virtue or Vice, for Rewards or Puniſhments, or any occaſion for a juſt or governing Providence; Man would be no better than an intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Machine, or a curious Piece of Clock-work, which, how true ſoever its Motions are, makes no Returns of Praiſe or Gratitude to the Author of it. And what a wild ſuppoſition is this, that to introduce a reaſonable Creature in the room of Angels and Men, excludes almoſt all the glorious Attributes of God, from having any thing to do in the Creation and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the rational World? But to come to the greateſt difficulty in the caſe before us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Prop.</hi> IV. God's Fore-knowledge of the Fall of Man cannot blemiſh his Goodneſs in creating him. It has been already proved, that God who is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely good might make a reaſonable Creature and a free Agent: and that it highly became him to do this, becauſe this was to make a Creature <hi>after his own Image,</hi> and that is the higheſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of creating Goodneſs; and one would think, this was enough to clear at once the Goodneſs and every other
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151439:62"/>Perfection of God, from the leaſt Defect or Error in the Creation of Man. But ſtill ſome Perſons are troubled to think that God ſhould intruſt Man with a Liberty of Choice, when he was infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libly certain beforehand that he would abuſe it; and this they apprehend to be inconſiſtent with perfect Goodneſs. But what Reaſon have they to think ſo? And what is their meaning by this Objection? Is it to blemiſh the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Man's Creation, or to clear the Goodneſs of God by denying his Preſcience? Do they mean to prove, that God did not create Men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and then leave them to their own Choice, to ſtand or fall, to be happy or miſerable? This they may be ſure he did not, if it was inconſiſtent with his Goodneſs: and if it was not, why are they troubled to think that he did do it? Or would they prove that God did not foreſee the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of creating a free Agent? Let them firſt anſwer all the Arguments, Affirmations, and Predictions in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which plainly prove that the free Thoughts and Actions of Men lie open and naked to the Preſcience of God; and then let them conſider what
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151439:62"/>they gain by excluding his Preſcience. Does it at all mend the matter to ſay, that God made innumerable Creatures that would ſin and be miſerable, but knew it not till it was too late to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it? or can they ſeriouſly allow themſelves to think, that he laid the Foundations of the Earth, and created Man upon it before ever he was <hi>maſter</hi> of his Deſign, or was ſure whether it would turn to account or not? How could he make a Covenant with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his Seed <hi>for ever,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 18.18, 19</note> and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from all the Families of the Earth, if he did not foreſee that <hi>his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren would keep the way of the Lord;</hi> or that there would always be a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Men in the World of the ſame Stamp and Integrity, that would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Worſhip and Service of the true God before the Pleaſures of Senſe, and ſignalize their Faith (as <hi>Abraham</hi> did) by the Freedom and Ingenuity of their Obedience to him? Let them. I ſay, impartially weigh the Conſequences on both ſides, and they will clearly ſee that they bear as hard upon the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, by denying his Preſcience, as they fear they ſhould do upon his Goodneſs, by aſſerting it.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:151439:63"/>
                  <p>Now to eaſe them of this Fear; that God's Foreknowledge of the Fall of Man was no blemiſh to his creating Goodneſs, will, I doubt not, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appear, if they candidly conſider theſe three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That his Preſcience had not the leaſt Influence upon their Fall or Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to him. Our firſt Parents might have lived and been eternally hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py upon the Stock of their original Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Endowments, and the Divine Favour reflected upon them, had they uſed them as they ought; and if they had done ſo, God had never foreſeen their Sin or Miſery. Neither did they ſin becauſe he <hi>foreſaw</hi> they would, but merely becauſe they <hi>would</hi> ſin: and therefore they would have ſinned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had foreſeen what they would do or not; and ſo their Fall could not in any reſpect be imputed to his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, no more than the Death of thoſe eighteen Perſons upon whom the Tower in <hi>Siloam</hi> fell,<note place="margin">Luk. 13.4.</note> was imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Eye that beheld the Falling of that fatal Tower. Now if the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of God had no Influence upon the Apoſtacy of his Creatures, his Goodneſs in creating them in a happy
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151439:63"/>State could be never the leſs for his Knowing that they would abuſe it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That his Foreknowledge of their Fall did not hinder him from uſing the moſt proper and likely means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it. When God made Man up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, he gave him power to ſtand and and perſevere in his Innocence, and to ſecure, improve, and immortalize his Glory and Happineſs; and when he had done this, he gave him a loud and timely warning of the great danger of Failing in his Obedience to him, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him that <hi>in the day of his Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion he ſhould ſurely die.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note> And is not this a fair Repreſentation of the Goodneſs of God in the utmoſt degree that became a wiſe, a holy, and a faithfull Creator? Does not this plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrate, that the making Man a free Agent was no Contrivance of his Creators to draw him into Sin or Miſery? And that his Preſcience was ſo far from ſerving any ſuch end, that it took the moſt natural and proper courſe to prevent it; admoniſht him of his imminent Danger, and foretold his <hi>dying day</hi> to be the ſame with that of his eating the forbidden Fruit? Which certainly God had never done,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151439:64"/>after he had put him into a way to live for ever, if either he had not foreſeen his Danger, or was willing to connive at his Death and Miſery. But more than this,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. God's Foreknowledge of Man's Abuſe of his Goodneſs was no real Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to it, becauſe it was in his power to turn that Abuſe to an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent end, and to take occaſion by our Fall to manifeſt the Glory of his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes in a far higher degree than was poſſible merely by his act of Creation. 'Tis the glorious Prerogative of God to bring good out of evil, which muſt have been concealed for ever, if he had never ſuffered evil to have entred into the World. The Glories of the Divine Wiſdom, Love, and Goodneſs in the Redemption of Mankind; the Glories of God's Patience, Mercy, and Juſtice towards the different Ranks and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Sinners, do all depend upon his Permiſſion of the Sins and Follies of Men, and applying ſuitable Remedies to them, and had never appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the <hi>Theatre</hi> of this World, if it had not been for the tragical Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages of our firſt Parents. The fall of Man was indeed a vaſt Unhappineſs
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151439:64"/>in it ſelf: but then it opened wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Scenes of happy and ſurprizing Providences,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.12</note> 
                     <hi>which the Angels</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>deſire to look into,</hi> and will be the Delight and Admiration of all good Men to Eternity. Above all, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of the Son of God (for which there would have been no occaſion in a State of Innocence) was a prodigious Demonſtration of his unparallelled Love and Favour to the lapſed Race of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, a ſtrangely proper and moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull means to <hi>reconcile the World unto himſelf,</hi> to promote Holineſs in ſeveral Inſtances, and Virtue in ſeveral Kinds, which could never have grown in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, and to advance the humane Nature far above the State and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty from which the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> fell. For the Union of the humane Nature with the Divine is not only an Argument of the ſincereſt Love and good Will to Men, but a moſt efficacious and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Principle of the higheſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and Happineſs that the Nature of Man is capable of. It is certain, the Recovery of Mankind required another kind of Diſpenſation than what was ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to a State of Innocence; and ſurely <hi>God</hi> would never have <hi>manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151439:65"/>in the Fleſh,</hi> or diſcovered ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Treaſures of Grace and Wiſdom in the Goſpel of his Son, but to exalt the Nature he took upon him to a more eminent Height, to enlarge our Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, and to make us <hi>Partakers of the Divine Nature,</hi> in a new and extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Meaſure, that (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) <hi>we might be filled with all the Fulneſs of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 3.19.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, if the Fall of Man was an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of greater Manifeſtations of the Glory of God, and his Love to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, than were poſſible in a State of Innocence, it certainly can be no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to his Goodneſs, when he had foreſeen, that he did not prevent his Fall. For what Reaſon is there, that the foreſeen Unhappineſs of a Creature, which is purely owing to himſelf, ſhould confine the infinite Goodneſs and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his Maker, who can as eaſily bring <hi>good</hi> out of evil, as a Creature out of <hi>nothing?</hi> Was the immenſe Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God exhauſted by his act of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation? or can his infinite Wiſdom find no other ways of expreſſing his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? Cannot he that made us after his <hi>own Image,</hi> create us a-new after <hi>the Image of his Son,</hi> without breaking
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151439:65"/>and diſſolving our Frame? Or can we think that when God foreſaw our Fall, he was not aware of the opportunities it gave him of magnifying his Grace and Goodneſs, his Wiſdom, Patience, Holineſs, Veracity, and Juſtice, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving and carrying on the ſtupendous Work of our Redemption? Nay who doubts but the Saints in Heaven are advanced to more eminent Degrees of Glory by the Merits of their Redeemer, than they could have been by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of their own Righteouſneſs, in caſe our firſt Parents had never fallen? In a word, God can ſerve his own wiſe and gracious ends by the Sins of Men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contributing to them; and ſince he can, and has taken care to raiſe us by our Fall to higher Capacities and Attainments in Virtue and Happineſs, than we enjoy'd or could have reacht in our former Station; it is I think a very plain and evident Truth, that God's Foreknowledge of our Fall was no blemiſh to his creating Goodneſs: or that his Goodneſs was conſiſtent with his Preſcience, as well as with all his other Perfections.</p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:151439:66"/>
                  <p>And now, I hope, I have ſaid enough to ſatisfie any candid inquiſitive Perſon,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That there was no Defect or Ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in the Creation of Man, or in his being made a reaſonable and free Agent, ſince he was created in a State of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence and Pleaſure, and wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to crown and complete his Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, but what depended on himſelf, the right uſe of his own Reaſon and Freedom, whithout which it was impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for him, or any other Being to be happy. Thus it became God to make him, and thus through his good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he was created: ſo that, after all the Ruins of Humane Nature, Man's <hi>original Frame</hi> ſtill ſtands as a glorious <hi>Monument</hi> of his Creator's Goodneſs, and will do ſo to Eternity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Fall of our firſt Parents from this good Eſtate was not owing to God's Foreknowledge of it, or any Act or Influence of his, or to any want of Power or Warning they might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have expected from him. And ſince their Fall can in no Reſpect be impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, we may be fully aſſured that his Goodneſs is not in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree diſparaged by his Preſcience or
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151439:66"/>Permiſſion of it. For is not he infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good to me, who puts it into my power to be happy, if I pleaſe, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver? And leſt I ſhould neglect my own Happineſs, kindly warns me of the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and diſmal Conſequence of it; tho' after he has done all that became him to prevent it, he ſhould not think fit to controul my Will, when he ſees me bent upon my own Deſtruction?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That we have abundant Reaſon to praiſe and adore the Goodneſs of God, who at firſt created us after his own Image, in all the happy and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Circumſtances, we could deſire for our ſelves; and when we had wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted our original Stock of Happineſs, was pleaſed to open the mighty Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of his Grace, and to give us new and ſurprizing Demonſtrations of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Love and Favour; by which we are infallibly ſure, that his Permiſſion of our Fall was grounded upon great and admirable Reaſons; and that God did not envy or neglect our Happineſs, or want any Kindneſs for us that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Creator and Preſerver of Men.</p>
                  <p>And here I ſhould conclude, were it not for one Objection which is apt to ſtick with ſome Perſons, whoſe Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151439:67"/>is chiefly deſign'd in this Paper: and that is this;</p>
                  <p>Seeing God is eſſentially good, might it not be expected that he ſhould have over-ruled the Will of Man, when he ſaw him warping from his Obedience to him, and ſo prevented all the Sin and Miſery, in which he has involv'd himſelf and his unhappy Poſterity?</p>
                  <p>This Objection I might fairly wave, having already ſaid enough to furniſh an Anſwer to it, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it does not lie againſt the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Creation (the Vindication of which is my proper Task) but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goodneſs of Providence, and indeed againſt the whole oeconomy of it. For if God ought to have prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the firſt Commiſſion of Sin, becauſe he is eſſentially good, for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he ought not to ſuffer Sin to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the World, having ever had the ſame power to hinder the <hi>Progreſs,</hi> which he had at firſt to prevent the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance</hi> of Sin into the World. On the other hand, if God, who is eſſentially good, was not obliged to hinder the firſt Tranſgreſſion, as I have formerly proved, neither is he obliged (farther than may ſerve the ends of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence)
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151439:67"/>to put a ſtop to the Progreſs of Sin and Wickedneſs.</p>
                  <p>But to ſpeak more directly to the Objection it ſelf; there is no doubt but the Will of Man is ſubject to the ſoveraign Will of God; otherwiſe God muſt have made a Creature that he was not able to govern, which is utterly inconſiſtent with the natural Notions of an infinitely wiſe Creator and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. But therefore the proper que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, whether it becomes ſo wiſe a Creator and Governour to over-rule the Will of his Creatures, after he has put them upon an eaſie Tryal of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to him, at leaſt in the ſame act on which the grand Iſſue of the Tryal depends? or, ſince God had given our firſt Parents a Liberty of Choice, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was ſuitable to his infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to hinder them by his irreſiſtible Power from chuſing and eating the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden Fruit? Now the Reſolution of this queſtion is not hard, if we conſider,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That God being infinitely wiſe, could not poſſibly loſe an opportunity to do that, which was moſt agreeable to his infinite Wiſdom and Goodneſs: and therefore ſince he did not hinder our Fall, when he did not want power
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151439:68"/>to do it, the Event undeniably proves that he did not eſteem it fit or prudential to interpoſe his irreſiſtible power, and by it to ſave us from the Guilt and Miſery which he ſaw us draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon our ſelves. There is nothing ſurer than that God, who looks thro' all the Natures, and comprehends all the Reaſons of Things, has always ſome wiſe and unanſwerable Reaſons for every thing he does, or does not do, or permits the doing of by others in the World; and then I am ſure no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more reaſonable than for us to acquieſce in all his Permiſſions, as well as in all the Diſpoſals of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and not think our ſelves wiſe enough to mend the Wiſdom and Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of them. A wiſe and good Man wants no Argument to convince him that any thing is wiſe or juſt, ſo far as infinite Wiſdom is concern'd in the Doing or Permiſſion of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the great Beauty and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Providence, and the moſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and equitable Rule of Government conſiſts in governing the ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Beings, according to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Natures; and then to rule a free Agent by mere Force and Compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151439:68"/>to give Man a Liberty of Choice, and not permit the exerciſe of it, muſt needs derogate from the Wiſdom and Beauty of his Providence: becauſe this is to govern his Creature contrary to the Nature he himſelf had given him, <hi>i.e.</hi> contrary to the natural and moſt equitable Rule of Government. For why were we made free, if our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor did not intend to leave us to our Choice? Is any Man the better for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forc't to do a good Action, or vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently reſtrained from a bad? A forced Obedience can never deſerve a Reward, or improve the leaſt habit of Virtue or Goodneſs in us; both which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon the free and ingenuous Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Will, exerting its own Liberty, and following the Light of Reaſon and Revelation, which is the true and only Perfection of it. Now, if a forc't Obedience could be no real Advantage to us, then it could not be expected from the Goodneſs of God that he ſhould have over-ruled the Will, and ſuppreſt the nobleſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple he had planted in the Mind of Man, only to extort a thankleſs Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience from him. But you will ſay, might not this have prevented his Fall?
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151439:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>I anſwer, Man had certainly ſinned, if he had not freely performed that ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and reaſonable Obedience his Maker required of him: and if he had, there would have been no occaſion of God's over-ruling his Will; and therefore there can be no Reaſon to object againſt his not doing of it. But ſuppoſe at laſt, that God had done this, and that Man had been under a Neceſſity of being innocent, (or rather of not ſinning) there could then have been no ſuch thing as true Virtue and Obedience in the beſt Eſtate that ever the World was in; which is ſuch a character of the Paradiſiacal State, and the Wiſdom of the Divine Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as can never be reconciled to the eſſential Properties of either.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Laſtly, It is a palpable Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Divine Perfections to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the Goodneſs of God ſhould oblige him to act contrary to the Rules of his Wiſdom; or that God ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge our firſt Parents of the Liberty of taſting the forbidden Fruit, upon the Penalty of Death, on purpoſe to prove their Obedience to him, and while they ſtood upon their Trial, render it utterly uſeleſs by his own Act, <hi>i.e.</hi> by determining their Wills contrary to
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151439:69"/>the Freedom and Inclination of them.</p>
                  <div type="conclusion">
                     <head>To Conclude.</head>
                     <p>There is one Meditation which me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks ſhould be ſufficient of its ſelf to revive the Spirits, and diſpell the Doubts and Fears of all diſconſolate Chriſtians, concerning the Creation of Men and Angels, and the Carriage of the Divine Providence towards them; <hi>viz.</hi> that there is an innumerable Company of bleſſed Angels and Saints in Heaven con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually adoring the glorious Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divine Attributes, admiring and celebrating, in joyfull Hymns and Anthems, the indiſſoluble Union and harmonious Conſiſtency of them; while we ſhort-ſighted Mortals, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a dark and penſive Vale, under the Clouds of Melancholy and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, are apt to fancy an unnatural War and Incongruity between them, and vainly diſquiet and perplex our ſelves about them. In Heaven we know there is and muſt be a right and perfect Underſtanding between all the bleſſed Inhabitants of that holy Place; and that there (as one that had been there tells us) <hi>we ſhall know as we are known;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.12.</note> and the mean while we may comfort our ſelves with this, that the excellent
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151439:70"/>Spirits above do all find their Happineſs in God's infinite Goodneſs to them, and are able to anſwer all Objections that we, or any of his Creatures, are able to frame againſt it.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <head>Some Books printed for <hi>B. Aylmer.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THirty Nine Sermons upon the Fifth Chapter of St. <hi>Matthew;</hi> being part of Chriſt's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the Mount. By <hi>Anthony Horneck,</hi> D. D. late Preacher at the <hi>Savoy.</hi> To which is prefix'd his Life, writ by the Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells:</hi> In two Vol. in <hi>8vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> no Free Aſſembly: more fully diſcover'd by a Collection of Letters and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the learned Dr. <hi>Vargas,</hi> and other great Miniſters, who aſſiſted at the ſaid Synod in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Poſts. Publiſhed from the Original Manuſcripts in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> which were procured by the Right Honourable Sir <hi>William Trumball</hi>'s Grand-Father, Envoy at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt. With an Introductory Diſcourſe concerning Councils, ſhewing how they were brought under Bondage to the Pope. By <hi>Michael Geddes,</hi> L. L. D. and Chancellor of the Cathedral Church of <hi>Sarum.</hi> In 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A brief State of the <hi>Socinian</hi> Controverſie, concerning a Trinity in Unity. By <hi>Jſaac Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> D. D. late Maſter of <hi>Trinity</hi> College in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> In 24<hi>'s.</hi> Price two Pence ſtitcht.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:151439:71"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
